  <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Borden's Grant</title>
          <author>Dr. E. Pendleton Tompkins</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Rockbridge Historical Society</publisher>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <bibl></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <front><p>At the second quarterly meeting of the Society, held in the Student Union building, on January 22, 1940, Dr. E. Pendleton Tompkins read the following paper on Borden’s Grant, a grant that included a large portion of Rockbridge County. See Frontispiece.</p></front>
      
      <body>
      <p>An old Scotch minister ascended his pulpit one Sunday morning, and announced his text in these words: Brethren, I will preach this day on the text found in the book of Hezekiah, umpty-steen chapter and such-and-such verse, which reads: “The devil goeth about like a roaring lion,” and my sermon will be divided into three parts, namely—and then following the good old Scotch custom of repeating the substantive each time before the pronoun, he continued — first, Who the devil he was; secondly, Where the devil he was going; and thirdly, What the devil he was roaring about.</p>
      <p>Following the example of this ancient of days, I will divide my paper into three parts. When we speak of Borden’s Grant” obviously there is implied a man by the name of Borden. The man referred to here was named Benjamin Borden; he hailed from New Jersey, and from this family the city of Bordentown probably gets its name. So we will discuss, first, Who Ben Borden was; second, Where Ben Borden was going, and third, What the d--- Ben Borden was r'aring about.</p>
      <p>
        As to the first, all that is now mown of him may be comprised in few words. As mentioned, he was a native or at least a resident of Jersey; he came to Virginia, as some say, first as an agent for Lord Fairfax. He made more than one journey to this state, or colony as it then was; he was a man of family, and acquired considerable property, and he made a Will mentioning the name of his wife, Zeruiah, and those of his nine children. More than this little is known of him, but he was undoubtedly a man of energy and ability.
      </p>
      <p>
        As to the second heading, viz: Where he was going. In the beginning of his known history he was in Williamsburg in the early decades of the 18th century, where he became acquainted with John Lewis, who had by then settled in the Valley of Virginia. Lewis invited him to visit his home in the Valley, and Borden accepted. While on a-hunting excursion with Lewis and his sons, it is said they captured a buffalo calf, which some days later Borden took with him to Williamsburg, and presented to Governor Gooch. This story is discredited by some historians, but must have
        had its origin in facts. This present was responsible, so it is said, for Governor Gooch interesting himself in securing for Borden a sizeable tract of land in the Valley.
      </p>
      <p>
        And this grant of land was the main thing which Borden was roaring, or r’aring about—this little matter of one hundred thousand acres of magnificent territory, forming a large part of our present county of Rockbridge. The casual way in which Governor Gooch handed out this grant and others of land he did not own, and which as yet was practically unexplored, reminds me of the story of the man who was sentenced by the Judge to.a twenty-year prison term; and remarked to-the sheriff as they left the court room: “He’s dam
        liberal with other people’s time, ain’t he!”
  </p>
  <p>
    Of course this is not fair to Governor Gooch, for he was acting in the capacity of Crown representative, and the Crown of England claimed vast territory beyond this locality. Besides, though he signed the Grant, the right to it was awarded Borden by the Council of Colonial Virginia, in an order which reads in part as follows: Benjamin Borden and William Robertson in behalf of. themselves and divers Masters of Families inhabitants of East Jersey setting forth that they are desirous to settle on the West Side of the great mountain on Sherrando River, and praying a grant of one hundred thousand acres of land to be laid out for them in one or more Surveys, beginning at or near that part of the great Mountains which is intersected by the South Branch of James River and running Southerly and Westerly to Complete that quantity. It is Ordered that the Petitioners have a Grant for the aforesaid quantity of land at the place above described upon condition that they settle one Family for each thousand Acres on the said Land within two years form the date herof and provided the same do not interfere with the Grant made to John Tayloe and Thos. Lee. Esqurs., with Wm. Beverly, Gent.</p>
    <p>
      As may be noted from the foregoing, the exact location of these lands was exceedingly hazy: the Order of Council merely gives a somewhat indefinite starting point - “at or near that point where the mountain is intersected by the South Branch of James River, and extending in southerly and westerly direction" — naming no other point of location for the very good reason that no other point was known, the lands never having been explored except perhaps very casually by daring adventurers. It was not until the Grant had been actually surveyed and laid off by a competent surveyor, and the “corners” marked—that is the various angles marked—that any more accurate description could be given. It speaks well for the knowledge and ability of the surveyor,
      who will be presently mentioned, that he was able to run lines many miles in their total length, and come so close to the amount of land granted, for when the lines had been established, and the acreage computed it was found to be 92,100 acres.
  </p>
  <p>
    And this brings us back again to the second heading, where was Borden going? The Order of Council was dated
    May 5, 1738, but Borden somehow let two years elapse before any settlers were actually on his land. His grant was about to lapse by reason of the time limit assigned. So he went again to the Council, as recited  in the minutes of this body, as follows: “... the petition of Benjn. Borden and Wm. Robertson * * setting forth the Unforeseen Accidents and difficulties which have prevented their seating the One Hundred Thousand acres of Land granted them on the West side of the Blew Ridge * * &amp; praying further time for Settling the said Tract,” etc. And the Council gave him an extension of time.
  </p>
  <p>He then set about vigorously to obtain settlers, sending agents to Europe to advertise his project. In the spring of the year 1737 he set out to investigate his domain. It is some-what remarkable that we find nowhere any mention of his partner, Wm. Robertson. We can only surmise that he must either have died, or have withdrawn from the venture, Borden was probably eager to see his land, but he was not a little handicapped by his ignorance of just where it lay, and how to locate it.
  </p>
  <p>
  But if he might expect to make good his claim he must
  find it, naturally. Consequently he took the plunge. Fate or
  good luck was on his side, because as he journeyed, and as
  night was about to overtake: him, he was fortunate in com-
  ing upon a party of pioneers making” camp for the night.
  He approached them and asked leave to stay the night at
  their camp. This part of the story is well told by one of these
  pioneers, namely, Mrs. Mary Greenlee, in her famous “Dep-
  osition”, made late in her lifetime, which is sometimes re-
  ferred to as “The Corner-stone of Rackboidge ‘History? ” She
  relates:
  </p>
  <p>
  “That she, with her husband, Ja ames Greenlee, iattlent in
  Borden’s Grant. * * That shortly before her settlement on
  said Grant, she, together with her husband, her father Eph-
  raim McDowell, then a very aged man, and her brother John
  McDowell, were on their way to Beverly Manor, and were
  advanced as far as Lewis’ Creek, intending to stop on Shen-
  andoah River, at that time never having heard of Borden’s
  tract. * * That about the time they were setting up their
  eamp in the evening, Benjamin Borden, the elder, came to
  their camp and proposed staying all night. In the course of
  conversation said Borden informed them he had 100, 000
  acres of land on the waters of James River, or the forks, if
  he could ever find it, and produced two papers (note .
  probably the two Orders of Council mentioned above,) aud
  satisfied the company of his rights. The deponent’s brother,
  _John McDowell, then informed the said Borden he would
  _ conduct him to the forks of James River for 1000 acres of
  land, and showed Borden his surveying instruments, etc.,
  and finally it was agreed that said McDowell should con-
  duct him to the grant, and she thinks a memorandum of the
  agreement was then made in writing. ‘They went thence
  to the home of John Lewis, who was a relation of deponent’s
  father, * * and there further writings were entered into, and
  it was agreed that they should all settle in Borden’s tract.
  That the said John. McDowell was to have 1000 acres for
  conducting them there, agreeable to the writings entered
  into, and that the settlers were to have 100 acres for every
  cabin they should build. * * * When the party came as they
  supposed into the grant, they stopped near a spring near
  where David Steele now lives, her brother and Borden went
  down the branch until they were satisfied it was of the
  waters of James River.” A “marker” erected at Mt. Carmel
  Church. by the Highway Department reads: “Near here the
  first settlers of Rockbridge county Behe their first camp
  in the county, 1737.”
  </p>
  <p>
    Borden and John McDowell ed as far . as the festa of

    South River and North River, “and having taken a course,
    returned to camp. ” This evidently was the starting point

    they fixed upon. Then Mrs. Greenlee continues: “They then.
    went to the place called Red House, where her brother John.

    built a cabin, and settled there’. Dr. Thurman has told us
    most entertainingly about the lente of this cabin, and
    why it was called Red House.
  </p>
  <p>Her account goes on to say: This was the first Lente ‘ot
  white people that ever settled on said grant. The said Bor-
  den remained on the grant from that time, as near as she
  can recollect, for perhaps two years or more, obtaining set-
  tlers, and she believes there were more than a hundred
  settlers before he left them. He was in the grant the whole
  time after first coming until he left it before his death.

  </p>
  <p>
    Just who were these settlers, that is the names of all of

    them, is not now available, but the names of many have

    _ been preserved. Richard Woods, Peter Wallace, J oseph Laps-
    ley, and John Bowyer, each had a family, and nearly all of
    them were related by blood kinship; and living to the im-
    mediate west and south of Lexington; the Alexanders and
    the McDowells, Greenlees, Stuarts, to the north; Matthews,
    Archers, Witleys, Telfords, to the southwest part of the county; Hern Walkers, toward the Beverly Manor tract;
    while Youngs, Campbells, Longs, Crawfords, Halls, Kerrs,
    and many other names still represented in. Rockbridge might
    be mentioned.
  </p>
  <p>The Rockbridge County News of January 8, 1940, re-
  prints an old petition, the very earliest document recorded
  in Rockbridge history, which gives names of many of these
  settlers, these earliest pioneers.
  </p>
  <p>Scanning the court records of the early jac which at
  this late day are practically all the records that have been
  preserved—we learn something of the character and the
  propensities of these pioneers, something of the fibre of
  which they were composed. On the whole they were a God-
  fearing people, they tried to live right, and to keep their
  fellowmen in the straight and narrow way. They were a
  stern race, hardy in body, keen in mind, and they undoubt-
  edly endeavored to live up to the moral code. As to the way
  they brought up their children, a little jingle has been
  penned which has probably more than a modicum of truth:

  “They raised them rough, they raised them well—
  When their. feet were set in the paths of hell,
  They put in their hearts the fear of God,
  And tanned their hides with a stiff ramrod!”
  </p>
  <p>They had strict laws, and they enforced obedience to the
  law. Numerous judgments of the courts are recorded, for
  example: Samuel Hulls presented for breach of the Sabbath
  by singing prophane songs. Called court on Elizabeth Smith
  for stealing—39 lashes. The King vs. George Lewis for driv-
  ing his wagon on the ‘Sabbath. Edward. McGarry, on sus-
  picion of felony, to stand in the pillory. Tom, a slave of
  - Robert Bratton, (this was in 1768) house-breaking and |
  horse-stealing, Convicted, 39. lashes and his ear cropped.
  Slave Hampton, house-breaking and larceny, convicted and
  sentenced to be hanged on the 30th inst. The death pay
  for stealing, mind you!
  </p>
  <p>
    Nor did they spare a man 3 ae of hhis prominence,
    as witness, John Bowyer—presumably the president of the justice’s court—disturbed the court by playing at “fives”;
    fined five shillings. A note is made in 1766: Sheriff is ordered
    to repair the pillory, and underpin the stocks. These were
    kept ready for use.
  </p>
  <p>
    Danger from lurking Indians was no baseless threat. It
    is said that some years ago a couple of boys were talking
    together, one being a McNutt, and the other a descendant
    of Mary Moore. The McNutt Jad said: One of ‘my relatives
    was tapped on the shoulder by the King’s sword, and he was
    made a knight—Sir Alexander McNutt. The other boy
    thought a minute, then said: Well, my great-grandfather,
    James Moore, was tapped on the head by an Indian chief,
    and that made an angel of him.
  </p>
  <p>
    Besides the menace of Indians, a constant fear, they were
    beset by an abundance of wild beasts—wolves and panthers
    probably being the worst. Bounties were paid for the heads
    of these creatures, in order to exterminate them as far as
    possible, and in November, 1751, the authorities paid for 225
    wolves killed inthe county.
  </p>
  <p>
    The appraisement of estates of deceased persons, that is
    a list of the decedent’s property with valuation of each item,
    occupies many pages of the records. On the whole this is
    rather dry reading, yet in contemplating what they had one
    can in a measure estimate what they accomplished. Many
    of the implements listed are wholly unknown to most peo-
    ple of the present day, for example, “hackle”, “scutching-
    knife”, “frow”, “dog-iron”, “dough-chist”, ete. In the ap-
    -praisement of the estate of Mrs. Mary Greenlee we note:
    14 sheets and 3 quilts, $25. These sheets were undoubtedly
    hand-woven of linen, raised on her own farm, the flax “ret-
    ted, scutched,and hackled,” then spun and woven beneath
    her own roof, and probably by her own hand. Also what is
    somewhat unusual: 6 silver teaspoons and sugar tongs, $5.00.
    Her estate—that is her personal property, totalled $2970.00
    . not an inconsiderable estate for that day. One noteworthy
    fact is that while domestic fowls as chickens, ducks, or tur-
    keys are never listed, they must have had such—yet geese are often included in these lists. This undoubtedly was be-
    caused geese furnished feathers for their feather beds, which
    were amongst their most prized POBeSMiOns, But why this
    invidious distinction?

  </p>
  <p>
    The matter of religious worship occupied a large place ~
    in the community life. The next thing after getting them-
    selves established, and a roof over their heads, was provid-
    ing a place of worship. So. it was that some of the churches
    in our midst today date back into that period. On May 20,
    1748 is recorded: “On motion of Matthew Lyle it was ordered
    certified that they had built a Presbyterian meeting-house
    at a place known as Timber Ridge; another at New Provi-
    dence; and another at Falling Spring”. A little later this
    record: On motion of Richard Woods, on behalf of himself
    and others, ordered that a Presbyterian meeting-house in
    Forks of James River in this county, be and hereby is re-
    corded as a place of pabiis worship, Monmouth or Hall’s
    meeting-house.
  </p>
  <p>Reading of the courageous aud peti PA men ‘ahi
  served these churches and. other pioneer churches, who
  made wearisome journeys, and braved the dangers ‘of the
  wilderness to. bring the word of God to their people, one
  can only wonder if the sense of duty faithfully performed
  was not nearly all the compensation received by them. It
  is safe to say that they certainly were not in the same cate-
  gory as-a-certain preacher of more recent date, as implied
  in this story. Three small boys were discussing finance; one
  said; My father can sit down and write a short piece, and
  get five dollars for it; the second spoke up: My father can
  go to the races and come back with a hundred dollars. The
  third could hardly wait to exclaim: Shucks! that ain’t
  nothin’; my father can get up in the pulpit, and preach a
  sermon, and it takes six men to carry the money to him!

  </p>
  <p>
    Another thing of community importance were mills,
    They began to raise grain at once—in fact Mrs. Greenlee
    mentions that her brother James McDowell had raised a
    crop of corn in Beverly Manor the year before they all set-
    tled on Borden’s lands. A mill is a prime necessity for converting grain into flour or meal, arid they were built early.
    The first was probably Hay’s mill in the northern portion
    of the county, and perhaps the second one built was that of
    James Young, on Whistle Creek, a couple ‘of miles from
    Lexington. The dam built on Whistle Creek for this mill is
    yet in existence, in fact in excellent state of preservation;
    the site of the mill itself is evidenced by two very sturdily-
    _ built pillars, which supported one side of the structure. Two
    or three members of this society recently visited this spot,
    and photographs were made by one of these gentlemen.
  </p>
  <p>
    Perhaps the statement that Borden had gotten his grant
    prior to all this, is misleading; for he only as yet had the
    promise of the lands. As a matter of fact his actual instru-
    ment of writing bearing the signature of Governor Gooch
    has as its date the sixth day of November, one thousand
    seven hundred and thirty-nine—that is more than two years
    after McDowell had made the survey.
  </p>
  <p>It would be far too tedious to enumerate the many “metes
  and bounds” of the Grant in this paper. Sufficient to say that
  four (4) of the “corners” are known and can be inspected
  by those who care to do so. Correspondence with a gentle-

  man of Augusta county in rather recent times, a man whom

  I have not yet met in person, tells me that he has located
  and identified some of the “corners” not very far from his
  home: this gentleman is Mr. Walter Kerr, of Route 3, Staun-
  ton. He writes interestingly, and portions of his letter being
  pertinent to our subject will be given. He says:

    </p>

  <p>
    “The first ‘squatters’ had nothing to show for their hold-
    ings except the blazed trees as lines of their so-called ‘toma-
    hawk rights’, till Benjamin Borden laid off the polygonal
    tract of 62 corners, beginning here at the 33d corner of Bev-
    erly’s ‘Manor’, and they both received their Patents from
    King George II of England. Then both Beverly and Borden
    could give the new settlers titles from the King’s Grant,
    which were better than their blazed enclosures of the first
    clearings merely. But the McDowells, the Paxtons, the
    Alexanders, the Grigsbys, the Greenlees, et als. of Bordens
    ‘tract of 92,100 acres, (and the King offered him more, for he visited George IJ, in person), and the Kerrs, Lewises,
    Pickenses, Bells, Crawfords, McCues, et als., of Beverly’s
    tract of 118,491 acres, through Lieut. -Governor Wm. Gooch,
    after the sabes of 1736 and 1739, and the King’s patent
    to Beverly and Borden,—all felt that their holdings were -
    more secure, and becoming matters of record, especially

    % after the first court of 1745, at “Beverly’s Mill Place”, now

    Staunton. These were almost purely. Scotch and so-called
    Scotch-Irish, and were not yet mixed with the Germans
    of the lower Valley.
  </p>
  <p>
    “Borden, Beverly, John Leis. ‘ahd Sallings, all came
    together down at Lewis’s “Bellefont” home, (now near
    Staunton), probably in 1736, and much planning was done,
    -we can imagine. Anyway, it seems that these pioneers were
    perfectly agreeable. This meeting. was after Salling’s Indian
    experience of some years, and some time after Lewis slew
    the Irish lord and escaped to America.”
    </p>
    <p>And Mr. Kerr goes on to say: “I have blue-prints of both
    the Beverly and the Borden tracts, which have four sides
    or courses in common. Iam enclosing a rough draft of them,
    but know they are familiar to you.” After Borden left the set-
    tlement, in 1739, as above stated, it would seem that he
    never came back, for his death occurred not many years
    later, that is in 1743. But a. new character appeared upon
    this stage in the meantime, this being a son of Ben Borden,
    _.who bore his father’ 5s name, and was known as Ben Borden
    the younger. He came to take charge of his father’s busi-
    ness, assigning lands to newly arrived settlers, and making
    titles. He, of course, came to know the McDowells, and while
    here lived in John McDowell’s family. But he had gone
    back to his father’s home in New J ersey before the occur-
    rence of a tragedy which threw a deep gloom over the
    entire settlement.
  </p>
  <p>
    This sad happening took place in December, 1742, and
    came about in this way: A certain party of Indians from the
    North, of the Iroquois tribe, came through the settlement,
    and some of them began marauding, killing animals which
    were the property of the whites, and making themselves
    objectionable. John McDowell had been appointed by the
    Governor a captain of militia in response to the before-
    mentioned petition, so it developed upon him to call out
    the militia, which he promptly did, to “escort” the red men
    beyond the bounds of this settlement. Dr. Thurman, in his
    paper at our other meeting, has told what happened; a
    pitched battle ensued at or near Balcony Falls, and McDowell with several of his men lost their lives.
      </p>
      <p>
        After the death of McDowell, and that of Borden, senior,
        which was not many months later, the younger Borden

        returned to the settlement, being now more than ever in- ~

        terested in the Grant. Under the English law of primogeni-
        ture he fell heir to all real estate, to the exclusion of his
        brothers John and Joseph, and their several sisters. In the
        court records of that day the first-born son is always designated as “eldest son and heir-at-law” of so-and-so. As expressed in the deposition, he was “full empowered under
        his father’s will to complete titles, and to sell land”. In the course of time he courted and married the widow of Mc-
        Dowell. Mrs. Greenlee has a restrained but slightly caustic
        comment to make on this; she says: Young Ben Borden came
        into the grant before her brother John’s death. “She recol-
        lects this from his being in ordinary plight, and such that
        he did not seem much respected by her brother’s wife, and
        when she (that is Magdalena Woods McDowell) afterward
        married him she could not but reflect upon the circum-
        stances.” And she goes on to say that young Borden “con-
        tinued to live at the same place where her brother settled
        as aforesaid until his death”. By this she refers to the death
        _ of Ben Borden, junior, as he contracted smallpox and died in 1753
        </p>
        <p>
          After the death of the younger Borden, another char-

          acter appears upon our stage, a man who was destined to  play an important part in the affairs of that early day.
          This was John Bowyer, who later became General John
          Bowyer. Of his birth and boyhood apparently little has been
          recorded. He appears first in this section some time in the
          1750’s, possibly not long after the death of Borden, junior. He came as a teacher, though how long he taught and ast
          where his school was located is not clear.
  </p>
  <p>After the lapse of some time he became the third fi
  band of Magdalena Woods, who had been the Widow Mec-
  Dowell, and then the Widow Borden, her new husband be-
  ing somewhat younger than herself. He took charge of her
  rather extensive interests, and apparently managed them
  to her satisfaction. In that remote day accounts and records
  were not accurately kept, and business seems to have been
  done in more or less haphazard fashion, that is as regards
  real estate ownership. Mrs. Greenlee, in. being interrogated
  when giving her deposition—she being ninety-five years
  old at the time—was asked this question: “Did not many
  persons, in the lifetime of the older Borden, settle in the
  Grant, under the expectation of getting land at the usual
  price, and without first contracting with Borden?” To which
  her reply was: “I think many settled before they had op-
  portunity of seeing Borden.” And. another. question was
  asked her: “Do you not believe the first deeds were made
  for the cabin rights?” To which she replied this was perhaps
  true. It was understood that building a cabin would entitle
  any pioneer to claim one hundred acres surrounding it.
  The inexactness of doing business in this way gave rise to
  endless law suits; suits were filed and cross-suits were filed,
  and they occupied the dockets of the courts for almost a
  full century, one generation taking up where the previous
  one left off, and witnesses having died, and documents lost
  or destroyed, gave rise to such a maze of uncertainty that
  finally the judge in the case ordered it swept from the
  docket. The records in “The Celebrated Borden Case” fills
  two large folio volumes in the record office in Staunton.

  </p>
  <p>General Bowyer occupied positions of trust and responsi-
  bility in Augusta county, later in Botetourt county, and
  finally in Rockbridge county, without having moved his
  home from one location. He built and lived in the place
  which is a landmark in this section, known as “Thorn Hill”,
  and his tomb is in the Lexington cemetery.

  </p>
  <p>The history of Borden’s Grant is that of a large section of Rockbridge county, for it was co-extensive with the entire northeastern portion; and the people who made its history are amongst the best, the progenitors of people of prominence not only in this state, but in many other far distant localities. The maze of relationship between the Woods arid the Wallaces, the McDowells, the Greenlees, the
    Grigsbys, and many others would require the anil of the
    best genealogists to trace and unravel.
  </p>
  <p>
    Oné of the hardships the young and musiacaeeblees in-
    clined generation had te encounter. was the difficulty in
    getting the matrimonial knot tied. The English laws about

    church matters were nothing less than onerous on the Val--

    ley people. For a long time there was no Church of Eng-
    land clergyman in this section, and the stringent mandates
    of the Crown would not permit the Presbyterian ministers,
    even when there was in the settlement such a minister, to
    perform the marriage ceremony. Mrs. Sampson, in her
    sprightly book, “Kith and Kin", gives an entertaining: ac-
    count of four young couples, all eight of them more or less
    blood kin to the others, cousins in some degree, making
    the trip to Orange Courthouse to get the nuptial knot tied.
    This was what they had to do, go all the way across the
    mountains to the county seat, for until 1745 this was a part
    of Orange county, after that year it was Augusta county.
    </p>
    <p>One of the earliest Presbyterian divines who was in this

    - section, as mentioned in Waddell’s “Annals of Augusta

    County”—though he did not become a resident, was Rev.
    Hugh McAden, who was visiting in the home of Joseph
    Lapsley, I believe, the day on which Braddock’s Defeat oc-
    - eurred, or when tidings of this disaster came to this region;
    he mentions it in his “diary” which is still extant, and speaks
    of the terror aroused by this news in the minds of the set-
    tlers, for they thought the Indians would probably exter-
    minate them. This was in the summer of 1756.
    </p>
    <p>The temptation to go into the family history of these
    ently settlers is great, but I must desist, for though highly
    interesting as was all that concerned them, their ways and
    means of making their homes and extracting a living in the
    wilderness, their church life, their community affairs, their
    mills, their forts against the Indians, the network of inter-
    marriage and blood relationship—all this would lead me
    into an endless recital, and I must forbear, and defer to
    some later date accounts of the “highlights” of the hardy |
    and daring Scotch-Irish who began the development of this
    magnificent region in which we are Privileged to live at
    this day and time.
  </p>
  <p>
    And now I will—in the 'eatisicag of legal writs—cease
    and desist, lest you begin to think I am the exemplification
    of the school-boy's definition of a circle, which he describes
    as a line which meets its other end without ending.</p>
  </body>
  </text>
  </TEI>