<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>
      The House Mountain Tragedy of 1846: A Digital Edition 
   </title>
   <author> Douglas J. Harwood</author>
   <editor> Robert S. Keefe</editor>
   <sponsors>Rockbridge Historical Society</sponsors>
      <respStmt>
         <resp>Encoded by: </resp><name>Toni-Marie Alibah '27</name>
      </respStmt>
  </titleStmt>
  <extent>
   1 KB
  </extent>
  <publicationStmt>
   <publisher> 
      Rockbridge Historical Society</publisher>
      <distributor>  Rockbridge Historiical Society</distributor><distributor> Washington and Lee University</distributor>
      <pubPlace> Lexington Virginia </pubPlace>
         <date>2009</date>
      <idno typle="ISBN">978-0-9777220-2-0</idno>
      <availbility> <p>© 2009 by the Rockbridge Historical Society</p></availbility>
  </publicationStmt>
  <seriesStmt> 
      <title> Proceedings of the Rockbridge Historical Society</title>
      <respStmt></respStmt>
      <bibScope unit="volume">XIII</bibScope>
  </seriesStmt>
  <sourceDesc>
      <bibl></bibl>

  </sourceDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc><p>Text encoded as part of DCI 295D: Dogotal Editions, Fall 2023</p></projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>TBD</editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>TBD</tagsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
 </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<standOff>
 <listPerson>
  <person xml:id="RHS-0001">
   <persName>Adam Schiff</persName>
   <occupation>District Attorney</occupation>
   <note>District Attorney for <placeName>Manhattan</placeName> in
       seasons 1 to 10 of <title>Law and Order</title>.</note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="RHS-0002">
   <persName>Mike Logan</persName>
   <note>
    <choice>
     <abbr>NYPD</abbr>
     <expan>New York Police
           Department</expan>
    </choice> Detective regularly appearing in
       seasons 1 to 5 of <title>Law and Order</title> and seasons 5 to 7
       of <title>Law and Order: Criminal Intent</title>.</note>
  </person>
  <place xml:id="LEX1" type="city">
 <placeName notBefore="1400">Lyon</placeName>
 <placeName notAfter="0640">Lugdunum</placeName>
 <location>
  <geo>37.784039624349134, -79.4452526675777</geo>
 </location>
</place>
<text>
   <front>
      <title>The House Mountain Tragedy of 1846</title>
      <bio>Doug Harwood is editor of the monthly Rockbridge Advocate, which he founded in 1992. A 1974 graduate of Washington and Lee University with a major in journalism, he has always been fascinated by Rockbridge history, especially if it is unusual and bizarre. He presented this paper on January 31, 2005, in Washington and Lee Uniersity’s Evans Hall.
      </bio>
   </front> 
      <body>
      <pb n="153"/>  
         <p>Not too long ago, the late <persName id="#RHS-0001">Henry Clark</persName> and his boy got in a gunfight with one of their neighbors up on Irish Creek. The fight was about a pig. And sheer cussedness.</p>
         <p>With that in mind, it is not beyond the realm of possibility that a killing on the saddle between the peaks of Big House Mountain and Little House Mountain in the winter of 1846 was caused by a squabble over a cow. And sheer cussedness.</p>
         <p>At least that’s what one of the neighbors said.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> had a bad reputation; there’s no doubt about that. He got caught in a bear-trap once while he was trying to steal some corn from the Sniders out in Rockbridge Baths. Tried the same thing again and was whipped for his troubles.</p>
         <p>In the summer of 1846, <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> was getting ready to bean Joseph Robinson with a rock. Why? Who knows? Sheer cussedness probably had something to do with it. Fortunately for <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Robinson, <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> got in the middle of it, grabbed <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson’s</persName> hand, and knocked him down.</p>
         <p>In court a couple of years later, <persName id="#RHS-0004">James Smith</persName> said he had told <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> to cut it out as Pettigrew had him on the ground. <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> calmed down a bit. <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> let him up.</p>
         <p>Some time after that, <persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith</persName> said, <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson’s</persName> cows went through a fence, got into Pettigrew’s cornfield, and wrecked it.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0005"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Anderson</persName> went down to <persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith’s</persName> house and asked <persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith</persName> and his wife, <persName id="#RHS-0006"> Nancy</persName> , to go with her and get the cows out of an old house they’d taken over after <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> had shooed them into it.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0004"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Smith</persName>, speaking for himself and his wife, declined the invitation. </p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Anderson</persName>, instead of taking a hint, went on a tear. “She abused <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> as a mean woman, and said that she could see her heart’s blood, and was not done with it yet.”</p>
         <p>On that cheery note, <persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith’s</persName> wife went part of the way back into the saddle of House Mountain with <persName id="#RHS-0005"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Anderson</persName>. And on the way, <persName id="#RHS-0005"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr>. Anderson</persName> embellished her chilling little oath. “She said she could see <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew’s</persName>heart’s blood run as free as she ever saw anything in her life.”</p>

      <pb n="154"/>
         <p>A couple of months later, in <date when="1846-10">October, 1846</date>, the old house where <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> had stashed the <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson’s</persName> cows was burned. And if <persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith</persName> is to be believed, when he asked <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> about the fire, <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> replied. “You all will see in a short time, the other house will go the same way.”</p>
         <p>Maybe a neighborly dispute over a cow did start it all. Maybe it was jealousy.</p>
         <p>Or maybe it was something else.</p>
         <p>I suppose if <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> and his wife, <persName id="#RHS-0007">Mary Ann Moore Pettigrew</persName>, had been among the prominent citizens of the county, we’d know pretty much everything there is to know about them and about just what happened on the night of <date when="1846-12-16">December 16, 1846</date>.</p>
         <p>But they weren’t. And what little we do know about them stems mostly from a horrible tragedy that happened in the saddle of House Mountain on the night of <date when="1846-12-16">December 16</date>, or <date when="1846-12-17">the morning of the 17th, in 1846</date>.</p>
         <p>Today nothing remains of the Pettigrew cabin — not a ruined foundation or chimney, not a marker, not anything. We don’t even know exactly where it was in the saddle.</p>
         <p>We can speculate a bit about the lure of the mountain, where the growing season is a few weeks longer than it is at lower elevations and where land prices, because of the isolation, were lower than they were down in the valley.</p>
         <p>But what brought the<surname>Pettigrews</surname> to Rockbridge County at all remains a bit of a mystery</p>
         <p>They arrived from Campbell County a few years before the tragedy. Just when, we don’t know, but there was talk of a fall from social and financial grace that preceded the move.</p>
         <p>We do know that <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> had a job at Tom Alphin’s distillery, about six miles away from the Pettigrew cabin as the crow flies.</p>
         <p>And we know that the Pettigrew cabin could be seen from at least three other cabins.</p>
         <p>Beyond that, we also know that a few days before the fire, <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> left his cabin along with his eldest daughter, <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName>. They apparently left on a Sunday, though one account pushed it forward to Wednesday. Some accounts said they had gone to visit some friends, but just whom those friends were remains a mystery. By other accounts, <persName id="#RHS-0003">John</persName> left to go to work at Tom Alphin’s whiskey mill.</p>
         <p>Just where <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName> stayed — and where <persName id="#RHS-0003">John</persName> stayed — are mysteries.</p>
         <p>In any event, on that December Tuesday, after <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0003">John</persName> had, by most accounts, left, a neighbor saw the Pettigrew cabin, smoke rising from the chimney. Nothing remarkable.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, it began to snow. And snow. And snow. Three feet of the stuff in all, by most accounts</p>
      <pb n="155"/> 
         <p>As the snow was ending on Thursday afternoon, another neighbor saw what looked like the cabin on fire. He didn’t think much about it. The <surname>Pettigrews</surname> had talked about moving, and the neighbor figured they had done just that, setting fire to the cabin before they left</p>
         <p>On Sunday afternoon,James Smith’s dogs began barking, and he went outside to see what the trouble was. He heard someone hollering in distress. It was <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName>. “He seemed to be out of breath, walking through the snow. He called and asked me to get some fire and go with him . . . that his house was burned and his family was all frozen.”</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0004">Smith</persName> got “some fire” — presumably coals or embers — and went with <persName id="#RHS-0003">John</persName>. When they got near the remains of the burned cabin, Smith came upon the gruesome sight that must have greeted <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> when he arrived home after walking for hours through the snow.</p>
         <p>He found the house burned and the bodies of <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> and five children lying close by. <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> was sitting on the end of some bed clothes, leaning forward, with a slit-bottom chair tilted forward against her back. Her head was leaning forward, bent over her only son, John, eight years old, who lay across her lap, dressed in only a shirt.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0009">Judith</persName>, the next-eldest girl after <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName>, lay on her side, four or five yards from her mother, one leg stretched out through the rungs of a chair and the other drawn up. She was in her nightdress and was wearing a pair of shoes. She was fourteen.</p>
         <p>The next girl, <persName id="#RHS-0010">Margaret</persName>, who was twelve, was sitting on a log leaning against a stump, her head hanging forward, her left foot under her, and her right foot stretched down in the ground and frozen in it. The ground had to be chopped with an ax to free Margaret’s foot.</p>
         <p>The other two girls, <persName id="#RHS-0011">Letitia</persName>, ten, and <persName id="#RHS-0012">Mary Elizabeth</persName>, six, lay at the root of a stump with their faces on the ground, opposite each other. They were in their nightdresses and shoes.</p>
         <p>There were no human tracks near the bodies. A set of animal tracks coursed back and forth to the spring. The Pettigrews’ dog had made them during a few quick runs for water. It was obvious from the tracks that the dog had, aside from those runs, stayed with the bodies.</p>
         <p>The bodies were blackened with ashes and dust from the burned-out cabin. One man said they were the color of iron.</p>
         <p>Word of the ghastly scene quickly got out, and before the day was out there were fifteen or twenty men on horseback at the scene, and another dozen or so came with wagons to haul the bodies away.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0013">Hugh Wilson</persName> was one of the men with a wagon. Two years later he recalled the snow drifting in the House Mountain saddle. He rememberedthe frozen bodies and the strange scene, with clothes blowing about in the snow — some within reach of the bodies. He remembered seeing a feather
      <pb n="156"/>
         bed about a hundred yards away from the smoldering ruins of the cabin. He remembered seeing the Andersons’ cabin, looking all cozy about 400 yards away. And he remembered hearing dogs barking in that cabin.</p>
         <p>But there was no sight of the <surname>Andersons</surname>.</p>
         <p>Other witnesses had other memories. <persName id="#RHS-0014">Polly Robinson</persName>, for instance, went up to the Pettigrew cabin before the bodies were taken away. She remembered seeing <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> sitting on a bed that was burned. <persName id="#RHS-0014">Polly</persName> figured the bed must have burned before <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> got on it. Near the girl who sat on the log was a basket of eggs, <persName id="#RHS-0014">Polly</persName> remembered. The basket and the egg shells were burned on the side facing the house.</p>
         <p>A coroner’s inquest took place the day after the bodies were discovered. The coroner, <persName id="#RHS-0015">Samuel Moore</persName>, had the bodies examined by two doctors, <persName id="#RHS-0016">Wilkenson</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0017">Rogers</persName>.</p>
         <p>“There were two wounds on <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName>,” they reported. “One was on her temple. The other on her throat. The wound on the temple was a bruise, apparently produced by the stroke of a stick. The neck seemed to have been grasped by a hand as to produce strangulation.”</p>
         <p>The conclusion: <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> had been murdered. There were no conclusions about what caused the deaths of the children.</p>
         <p>The <surname>Andersons</surname> were likely suspects. There had been that spat over the cow. There was <persName id="#RHS-0002"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Anderson’s</persName> general reputation, which was not good. And there was the matter of some linens that were found in the Anderson cabin — linens that neighbors had first seen at the Pettigrew cabin. (<persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> later swore that the linens, a coverlet and a tablecloth, belonged to his wife, <persName id="#RHS-0005">Mary</persName>.)</p>
         <p>The <surname>Andersons<surname> didn’t exactly cooperate with the investigation.</p>
         <p>While the bodies were being chopped out of the snow and ice, <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> left for Billy Brain’s place, a few miles away, and then went on to Augusta, where he stayed for a week or two. <persName id="#RHS-0005">Mary Anderson</persName> and her two daughters were apparently still home when the Pettigrew bodies were being carted down the mountain; <persName id="#RHS-0005">Mary</persName> told one woman who stopped in that the <surname>Pettigrews</surname> had been killed.</p>
         <p>But within a few days, the entire <surname>Anderson</surname> family left the county. Just where they went is not known. Two years later, they turned up in New Castle, about thirty miles southwest of House Mountain, in Craig County. A certain <persName id="#RHS-0018"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Tilson</persName>, who apparently was boarding them, told them he had gotten a letter from Rockbridge saying that the <surname>Andersons</surname> had murdered a family, and that he’d better leave or he’d be abused. Confronted with the allegation, <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> replied that if he had murdered a family, he was “as good as the people of New Castle or Bedford.”</p>
         <p>Just what that meant, who knows? But the odds are good that at least some of the people of New Castle and Bedford had heard about the kill      
      <pb n="157"/>
         ing. The <surname>Andersons</surname> were illiterate, but it would have been hard to avoid some talk. After all, the tragedy was serious news.</p>
         <p>The Richmond Enquier had reported it under the simple headline, “Awful Casualty”:</p>
         <p>It has never before been our duty to publish the account of so awful an accident, as that, the details of which have just been related to us: the facts as we can learn them from the neighbors are there: During the last week, <persName id="#RHS-0003"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> John Pettigrew</persName>, a decent and Industrious citizen of our county, left his house in company with his eldest daughter upon a visit to some of his friends at a distance, his wife and five other children remaining at home. On Sunday he returned and found his house burnt to the ground, and upon looking around he discovered all of that family which he left in fancied security lying dead together at a short distance from the ruins of his house. They were all partially burned, but it is supposed that they must have frozen to death after they fled the house, as the burns were not supposed to have been severe enough to have caused death. What a reception for this poor laboring man! Instead of finding, as he expected, that family, the comfort of his Life, nestled together around the family fireside, he finds them a heap of blackened and stiffened corpses. It is heart sickening in the extreme, and we hope that it may be long before we shall be called upon to record such another casualty.</p>
         <p>P.S. Since the above was in type we have learned that these unfortunate persons were very slightly burned, and that the whole of them were found within fifteen or twenty feet of the ruins of the house,</p>
         <p>The Valley Star, published in Lexington, said, under the headline, “A Shocking Calamity”:</p>
         <p>On Thursday night last, the house of a <persName id="#RHS-0003"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> in the hollows of the House Mountain, about seven miles from this place, was burned to the ground. The next morning <persName id="#RHS-0007"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr></persName> Pettigrew and five children were found burned and frozen to death. The corpses of the children, we understand, were lying strewed around the mother in the snow and she, in a leaning attitude over her infant child, as if striving to protect it from the cold. The husband and one of the children were absent from home. The dreadful calamity happened the night after the terrible snow storm mentioned in another article in this paper, We never have heard of such a melancholy occurrence as this taking place in our normally quiet community. A whole family swept away in a single night, perishing in the fire and the snow, remote from any other habitation, with no human eye to witness the sufferings and cries for relief, and awakening no doubt from the soundest sleep, to find themselves enveloped in flames. None are left to tell the particulars of their melancholy end, but the origin of the fire is supposed to have been accidental. The family we learn are poor, but quite respectable. How strongly does this melancholy case appeal to our sympathy
      <pb n="158"/>
         especially on behalf of the child, who was spared from the same death as the others by absence from home. Let those who are protected from the severities of winter by an abundance of the world’s goods remember the poor, and watch over the comforts of the lonely survivors of this ill-fated family.</p>
         <p>The Lexington Gazette’s version of the story was the only one to hint at murder, though its accounts of the coroners’ report do not completely agree with the version of the report that was later introduced in court.</p>
         <heading> A Mother and Five Children Dead!</heading>
         <p>The feelings of this community were never more severely shocked then when, a few days since, it was announced that a mother and five children were found within a few feet of the ashes of a cabin, cold and stiff in death. The name of the family was <surname>Peticrew</surname>.* They removed to this county about two yeurs since, from Campbell. They were once in easy and prosperous circumstances, but misfortune had stripped them of their all; and they sought and found an humble home amid the mountains of Rockbridge. No one would be with them long without discovering that they had seen better days. and they soon gained for themselves the respect and sympathy of all the virtuous and good who made their acquaintance.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0003"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> John Peticrew</persName>, the husband and father of this unfortunate family, was absent some miles from home, pursuing his weekly toil as a day laborer, and owing to the deep fall of snow which occurred on Wednesday night, did not, as was his custom, seek his home on Saturday night, but deferred it until Sabbath morning. When within a few hundred yards of the fatal spot, as the writer is informed, he picked up on the snow a half-burnt sheet of paper, which he immediately recognized as belonging to himself. Fears were, at once excited, and with trembling heart he hastened to see whether the tale this halfburnt sheet had told him were true. He soon saw the chimney, but the house was gone. A few steps more brought him in sight of the lifeless remains of wife and children. They were lying near each other and from 10 to 15 feet from the ashes of their dwelling. What must have been the feelings of the husband and the father with such a scene before him?</p>
         <p>It is generally believed that the burning occurred on Wednesday night — the night of the snow storm. The house was seen on Wednesday, and no traces discoverable in the snow to tell that it happened after the storm. The house was situated between the two House Mountains, and within three or four hundred yards of another, but not within sight. <persName id="#RHS-0002"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Peticrew</persName> was himself the first to discover this awful calamity and his sad bereavement.</p>
<horizontal line></horizontal>

<note>* Various documents contain variant spellings of the name.</note>
<pb n="159"/>
         <p>The dead bodies were removed on Sabbath evening to the house of <persName id="#RHS-0019"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> William Wilson</persName>, where an inquest was held by the coroner, <persName id="#RHS-0015"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Samuel R. Moore</persName>, on Monday. The verdict in the case of <persName id="#RHS-0007">Mary Anne</persName> — the wife and mother was, in substance, that she came to her death by violence — whether accidental or inflicted by the hand of some person unknown is uncertain. A wound was discovered on the side of her forehead and extending behind the ear, as if inflicted by a blow from a stick. Marks of violence were also discovered on her throat, knees and legs.</p>
         <p>The verdict in the case of the children, <persName id="#RHS-0009">Judith Anne</persName>, <persName id="#RHS-0010">Margaret June</persName>, <persName id="#RHS-0011">Letitia</persName>, <persName id="#RHS-0020">John Thomas</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0012">Mary Elizabeth</persName> — the youngest of whom was about six years, and the oldest 14, was that they came to their death by freezing. These were all deposited in the same grave on Tuesday the 22nd, at Old Oxford Church — attended by a throng which evinced the deep sympathy that was felt by the community for surviving friends in this sore affliction.</p>
         <p>A meeting was called forthwith, and measures taken to erect a monument over the cold remains of the mother and children which should tell to posterity the sad tale, over which so many wept that day.</p>
         <p>The eldest daughter of <persName id="#RHS-0003"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Peticrew</persName> still survives. She was at her grandfather’s on the night of the sad catastrophe.</p>
         <p>After the initial burst of stories, which were reprinted in papers all over the state and beyond. the catastrophe vanished from the record. In <date when="1848-08">August 1848</date>, nearly two years alter finding his family dead in the snow, <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> died — legend has it from a broken heart — and was buried at Oxford.</p>
         <p>Another two-and-a-half years passed. And then, in <date when="1851-03">March, 1851</date>, there was this, as recorded by the Gazette:</p>
         <lexgazette>
         <heading> Arrest for Murder</heading> 
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002">Jas. Anderson</persName>, his wife, and two daughters were arrested last week in Botetourt County and committed to jail in this place under the charge of committing a murder in this county about five years ago. The circumstances are these. A family named <surname>Pettigrew</surname>, living in the neighborhood of the House Mountain, consisting of a mother and five children were found dead in the winter of 1846. The house in which they resided was burned down and the corpses frozen when found. Marks of violence were found on the mother and the eldest daughter, but none on the rest.</p>
         <p>Those marks consisted of a scar on the side of the head and the print of fingers on the throat of the mother and similar marks on the throat of the daughter. A deep snow fell on the night the event is supposed to have happened, but no snow was found on the corpses and
   <pb n="160"/>
         no tracks around the place of occurrence. Several neighbors resided within a half and three quarters of a mile off, to whose residence there existed no obstruction unless is was the snow of this occasion. Suspicion fell on this Anderson family at the time. They then resided within three quartets of a mile of the place. The matter has slept for five years now and the evidence which led to the arrest of these parties will be developed at their trial at the April term of our monthly court.</p></lexgazette>
         <p>The only account of what led to the arrest is found in a newspaper article from 1902, which says that Anderson had confided in a man named <persName id="#RHS-0021">Andrew Taylor</persName>, and that <persName id="#RHS-0021">Taylor</persName> had blabbed to a man named <persName id="#RHS-0019">Wilson</persName>, and that <persName id="#RHS-0019">Wilson</persName> had passed the story along to <persName id="#RHS-0022">Sampson Moore</persName>, who was <persName id="#RHS-0015"><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Pettigrew’s brother</persName>.</p>
         <p>(<persName id="#RHS-0021">Taylor</persName>, <persName id="#RHS-0022">Moore</persName>, and three <surname>Wilsons</surname> testified for the prosecution during the trial. <persName id="#RHS-0023">Billy Brain</persName>, to whose house <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> had initially fled, was never called as witness. Neither were the <surname>Alphins</surname>, who ran the distillery between Short Hill and House Mountain where <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> said he was working when his family died. <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel Pettigrew</persName>, the sole survivor of the family, did testify, though what she said in court was not recorded. Most later accounts say that she had left home with her father in order to stay with her grandmother, who was ill; she was not with him when he returned to the cabin to find his family slain.)</p>
         <p>As for a possible motive, there were the wandering cows. And there were claims of thievery. <persName id="#RHS-0022">Sampson Moore</persName> had discovered one of his sister’s blankets in Anderson’s cabin — so he said.</p>
         <p>If <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> had anything to say about the cows, it was not recorded. But a sworn statement by <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> dismissed the stolen blanket and linen claims.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> said he had witnesses who would say “that one coverlet and one table cloth. which it is alleged, was the, property of Pettigrew. was the property of . . . [<persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName>], and that the said articles of property was in the possession of and was the property of . . . [<persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName>] several years previous to the time when the said Pettigrew’s house was burned and his family came to their deaths. and that the said coverlet was woven by . . . [<persName id="#RHS-0005">Nancy Anderson</persName>] and that said table cloth was presented to his said wife by <persName id="#RHS-0024">Peggy Chandler</persName> . . . .”</p>
         <p>The trial, initially set for <date when="1851-04">April 1851</date>, was delayed a month so that Anderson’s witnesses could be rounded up.</p>
         <p>Two of the state’s witnesses, <persName id="#RHS-0025">Thomas Moore</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0022">Sampson Moore</persName>, were brothers-in-law of <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName>. And before <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> moved to Rockbridge with his family in 1844, the <surname>Moores</surname> had been involved in a fight of their own with <surname>Pettigrew</surname></p>
      <pb n="161"/>
         <p>It was all about money, and it began in Campbell County, following the family to Rockbridge. The long and short of it was that <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> claimed his father-in-law, <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persname>, owed him $10,000, and <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persName> said he didn’t.</p>
         <p>Dueling suits were filed in Rockbridge County Circuit Court — <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persName> versus <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Pettigrew</persName> and others and <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> versus <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persName> and others — in addition to an earlier suit filed in Campbell County.</p>
         <p>The records concerning the suits are a little murky. but apparently <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> bought a pair of judgments against <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persName> from the estate of a <persName id="#RHS-0027">John Hancock</persName> in the late 1830s.</p>
         <p>In a deposition, a friend of Pettigrew testified, “I heard <persName id="#RHS-0003"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Pettigrew</persName> say that he had bought the claim [against <persName id="#RHS-0026">Moore</persName>] . . . for the benefit of <persName id="#RHS-0026"><abbr>Mr.</abbr> Moore</persName> to keep peace between him and his son and said that if that was all the debts he had named to him he would have money enough left to buy him a right smart plantation; and he didn’t charge him anything for what he had done for him.”</p>
         <p>But <persName id="#RHS-0026">Predham Moore</persName> claimed <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> bought the judgments — worth roughly $3,000 — for fifty cents on the dollar with money from payments which Moore had already made on those judgments. And <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName>, whatever his intentions might have been when he bought the judgments, had the sheriff seize Moore’s seven slaves when Moore defaulted. (The slaves were <persName id="#RHS-0028">Tom</persName>, age fifty; <persName id="#RHS-0029">Amy</persName>, twenty-five; <persName id="#RHS-0030">Sarah</persName>, fourteen; <persName id="#RHS-0031">Susan</persName>, eight; <persName id="#RHS-0032">London</persName>, six; <persName id="#RHS-0033">Ben</persName>, three; and <persName id="#RHS-0034">Amy</persName>, an infant.)</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0026">Moore</persName> apparently managed to halt the auction of the slaves. But the dispute dragged on for several 1846, seven months before the horror in the saddle of House Mountain.</p>
         <p>There is nothing in the record to indicate that the Andersons were connected with the Pettigrew—Moore squabble. But the family was apparently split over the suits, with two of Pettigrew’s brothers-in-law, <persName id="#RHS-0025">Thomas</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0035">Camel</persName>,* siding with him, and with a third brother-in-law, <persName id="#RHS-0022">Sampson Moore</persName>, against him. And
      <note>* That was really his name.</note>
      <pb n="162"/>
         five years after Pettigrew’s family was found dead in the snow, it was <persName id="#RHS-0022">Sampson Moore</persName> who told the authorities that <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> had confessed to a friend of a friend.</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002">James</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0005">Mary Anderson</persName> were indicted, charged with the murders of the Pettigrew children, as well as that of their mother. There is nothing in the official court records of the Andersons’ trial — other than a boiler-plate allegation in the indictments that the <surname>Andersons</surname> were possessed by the devil — that sheds any light on why <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> would have wanted to kill the Pettigrew family. Nor is there anything in the court records to confirm newspaper accounts that the Anderson children were ever formally charged with anything in connection with the alleged murders.</p>
         <p>The trial began on <date when="1851-04-16">April 16, 1851</date>, and lasted six days. The <surname>Andersons</surname> hired three lawyers: <persName id="#RHS-0036">Samuel Letcher</persName>, <persName id="#RHS-0037">L. F. Paxton</persName>, and <persName id="#RHS-0038">Robert Doyle</persName>. There is no record of what the lawyers were paid, or who paid them. The jury was sequestered for the entire trial, which was nearly unheard of in Rockbridge in those days.</p>
         <p>Three newspapers published basic accounts of the trial. Two of those newspapers dropped tantalizing hints about the reportage in the third, but if a copy of that third account, in the Rockingham Register, still exists, it cannot be located.</p>
         <p>The Lexington Gazette article said:</p>
         <p>This mysterious and deeply interesting trial for murder was commenced at the term of our Superior Court, on Wednesday the 16th inst., in which <persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson</persName> and his wife were arraigned for the murder of the <surname>Pettigrew</surname> family on the night of the 16th of <date when="1846-12-16">December, 1846</date>. The trial was closed on <date when="1851-04-22">Tuesday, the 22nd</date> inst., and the verdict of the jury rendered, that <persName id="#RHS-0002">Jas. Anderson</persName> was guilty of murder in the first degree, and his wife acquitted thereof. A new trial was applied for on behalf of the prisoner and granted by the judge, and the venue changed to the County of Bath.</p>
         <p>The testimony proved that the house in which the deceased resided was seen standing Wednesday evening, the <date when="1846-12-16">16th of December, 1846</date>, at about dark — that a large light was perceptible on the same night, in the direction of the house, between the hours of seven and eight o’clock — that the next morning the chimney of the house was discovered remaining, by a witness some distance off.</p>
      <pb n="163"/>
         <p>That it commenced snowing on the evening of <date when="1846-12-16">December 16th, 1846</date> at sundown and continued until about 10 o’clock the next day, that the snow was about three inches deep between the hours of six and eight o’clock that night, and sixteen inches deep when it ceased the next day.</p>
         <p>That the dead bodies of the deceased, six in number, were found in a frigid state on the morning of the ensuing Sabbath. That the ground was entirely clear of snow for twenty-five feet beyond the house in the direction of the dead bodies, and that the location of the bodies was about fifteen feet from the foundation of the house, and about ten feet from the edge of the snow towards the house. But the bodies were not burned. Nor were any tracks to be found either in the snow or where the ground was clear of snow around the burnt house. The burning of which may have made the ground soft by the melting of the snow, No snow was found upon the bodies or upon any of the articles carried out of the house, Wearing apparel and bed clothes wore found there, but the bodies were only partially dressed and entirely unprotected by the bed clothing. Some of them were in a recumbent position and others prostrate. The foot of one of them was sunk in the ground and frozen tight. No marks of violence were found upon any of them except the mother, who had a wound upon her temple and impressions upon the neck similar to those made by pressure from the hand.</p>
         <p>The eyes of the oldest child, a daughter about 16, were stretched open, and cast as if looking back. The countenances of the rest indicated no apparent marks of disfiguration. The testimony tended to show that the night was not remarkably cold, particularly in the early part, and that the houses of several neighbors were accessible, some of them within a half-mile, and some three quarters of a mile off.</p>
         <p>We make the above narration of mysterious circumstances merely in deference to the corpus delicti, and with an impartial hearing as to the hypothesis of the guilt or innocence of the prisoner. We have heretofore announced our intention of publishing the proceedings of the trial in full, but inasmuch as the prisoner is to have a new hearing, we are constrained from a sense of justice to refrain from such publication now</p>
      <pb n="164"/>
         <p>A certain anonymous correspondent, however, of the Rockingham Register, has furnished that paper with a garbled report of the testimony purporting to be from the records of the examining court, which is going the rounds of our exchange papers, and which was brought to the notice of the court publicly, and such an exposition made of it as to leave the author in a most unenviable position.</p>
         <p>The Valley Star, owned by one of Anderson’s lawyers’ brothers, added:</p>
         <p>We refrain from publishing the testimony in the case for the reason that we desire the accused — degraded and debased as he is — to have a fair trial before another jury composed of men who will know nothing of the facts except as narrated to them by the witnesses.</p>
         <p>We will express no opinion as to the guilt or innocence of <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName>. A jury of twelve impartial men, after hearing the evidence in the case and the arguments of counsel, were unanimous in their opinion that the <surname>Pettigrew</surname> family came to their death by the hand of felonious violence, and that <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> was the guilty felon. A judge who bears the character of a profound lawyer, and an honest man, set aside the verdict upon the ground that the deceased died of accidental freezing and no murder has been committed.</p>
         <p>One damning piece of evidence came from a witness who said that 
         when the ruined cabin where <persName id="#RHS-0003">Pettigrew</persName> had kept Anderson’s cows burned, <persName id="#RHS-0002">Anderson</persName> said, “You all will see the other house go the same way.”</p>
         <p>Another came from a witness who said that when the party came to haul the bodies away, Anderson had emerged from his cabin, drunk, and shouted for them to go away, saying he hadn’t “finished.”</p>
         <p><persName id="#RHS-0002">James Anderson’s</persName> second trial was set for the <date when="1851-09">September 1851</date> term of court in Bath County, far beyond the pens of any newspaper correspondents. It was delayed for a full year. In the end, eighteen witnesses were summoned, including <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel Pettigrew</persName>, the surviving daughter. Three of Anderson’s witnesses didn’t show up at all. Two of the Commonwealth’s showed up drunk and were jailed for it. Aside from a notation in the Rockbridge court record that was sent to Bath, there is not the slightest indication in the official records as to what happened at the trial. That notation reads, simply, “We the jury find the prisoner not guilty . . . .”</p>
      <pb n="165"/>
         <p>Two weeks after the trial, one of Anderson’s attorneys was arrested for gambling in a card game on the streets of Lexington. By then, his client had left town and moved to Craig County.</p>
         <p>Three years after the trial, in <date when="1855-12">December 1855</date>, <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel Pettigrew</persName> married <persName id="#RHS-0039">James G. Reynolds</persName> and set up housekeeping on Kerrs Creek. They had two daughters, <persName id="#RHS-0040">Mary Ann</persName> and <persName id="#RHS-0041">Sarah</persName>. But before the younger was born, <persName id="#RHS-0039">James Reynolds</persName> died. <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName> never remarried, and raised her two children. She lived to a ripe old age, seventy-eight, and in her later years lived in Collierstown with her daughter, who had married <persName id="#RHS-0042">John Mackey Knick</persName>. <persName id="#RHS-0008">Rachel</persName> died in <date when="1908-10-08">1908</date> and was buried in the Collierstown Presbyterian Church Cemetery.</p>
         <p>Her father, mother, four sisters, and brother are buried in the Oxford Cemetery nearby. The monument that marks their graves is the second erected in their honor. Legend has it that the first was blasted to smithereens by lightening in 1902, but a spoilsport newspaper account said that it was made of wood and simply rotted away.</p>
         <p>In any case, the monument doesn’t mention murder. It says:</p>
         <line>In memory of a mother and five children</line>
         <line>who perished in the snow storm of the <date when="1846-12-17">17th December, 1846</date>,</line>
         <line>between the House Mountains.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0007">Mary Ann Moore</persName>, wife of <persName id="#RHS-0003">John Petticrew</persName>,</line>
         <line>Aged 41 yrs. &amp; 10 mo.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0009">Judith Annie</persName>, aged 14 yrs. &amp; 7 mo.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0010">Margaret Jane</persName>, aged 12 yrs. &amp; 10 mo.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0011">Letitia</persName>, aged 10 yrs. &amp; 11 mo.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0020">John Thomas</persName>, aged 8 yrs. ars &amp; 4 mo.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0012">Mary Elizabeth</persName>, aged 6 yrs. &amp; 3 mo.</line>
         <line>The husband and father on his return three days after</line>
         <line>the sad event was the first to discover that his house</line>
         <line>was in ashes and his wife and five children cold in death.</line>
         <line><persName id="#RHS-0003">John Petticrew</persName></line>
         <line><date when="1805-02">Feb. 1805</date>, <date when="1848-08">Aug. 1848</date></line>
         <line>This monument was erected by a sympathising community in 1847</line>
         <line>Replaced by the citizens of Collierstown &amp; Buffalo</line>
         <line>1902</line>
      </body>
</text>
</TEI>

                
