<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>A Twentieth Century Highway Story: A Digital Edition</title>
   <author>Gen. James A. Anderson</author>
   <editor>Rockbridge Historical Society</editor>
   <sponsor>Rockbridge Historical Society</sponsor>
   <respStmt>
      <resp>Encoding by: </resp><name>
      Zach Cruet '27</name>
   </respStmt>
  </titleStmt>
  <extent>
<!-- Extent of digital XML file--></extent>
  <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Rockbridge Historical Society</publisher>
      <distributor>Rockbridge Historical Society</distributor>
      <distributor>Washington and Lee University</distributor>
      <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
      <date>1961</date>
      <availability>Rockbridge Historical Society</availability>
  </publicationStmt>
  <seriesStmt> 
      <title>Proceedings of the Rockbridge Historical Society</title>
      <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
  </seriesStmt>
  <sourceDesc>
   <bibl>
      
   </bibl>
  </sourceDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc><p>Text encoded as part of DCI295D: Digital Editions, Fall 2023</p></projectDesc>
     <editorialDecl>TBD</editorialDecl>
     <tagsDecl>TBD</tagsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
 </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
  <front>
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <div type="subsection" n="1">
      MINUTES OF OCTOBER 31, 1960 MEETING
    </div>
  </div>
<p>The regular fall meeting of the <org>Rockbridge Historical Society</org> was held at the Castle on <date when="1960-31-10">October 31</date> and was very well attended in spite of the heavy downpour of rain. Col. Brooke presided.</p>
<p>The minutes of the Executive Meeting held <date when="1960-17-10">October 17</date> were read and approved.</p>
<p><abbr>Dr.</abbr> Turner reported that the Castle library had been enlarged and that the books acquired last year (about <num type="cardinal" value="100">100</num>) had been catalogued. A collection of old and interesting school books presented to the Society by <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Leslie Campbell were on display. <abbr>Dr.</abbr> Turner also showed the members an election cartoon of <date when="1860">1860</date> which is on permanent loan to the Society.</p>
<p>Col. Brooke read a letter from the State Chamber of Commerce forwarded to him by Don Huffman of the local Chamber of Commerce asking for materials from this area to be used by Thalhimers Department Store of Richmond in a window display of Civil War interest. Col. Brooke asked members for suggestions.</p>
<pb n="96"/>
<p>A letter was also read from <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Lawrence Smail, a talented artist now living in Lexington, offering to paint old homes and places of historic interest in the county.</p>
<p>Col. Brooke read a letter from Major Chester Goolrick, a member of the Rockbridge County Centennial Committee asking if the Society would be interested in staging a ceremony at the Court House to commemorate the point at which the first local troops departed for the War between the States. A suitable marker would also be erected. Col. Brooke stated that he would appoint a committee to work out plans and that <abbr>Dr.</abbr>James Connor of the <choice><expan>Virginia Military Institute</expan><abbr>V.M.I</abbr></choice>History Department had agreed to be Chairman of this committee. <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> Flournoy was suggested as consultant to the committee and <abbr>Mr.</abbr> Houston Barclay was also mentioned.</p>
<p>Col. Brooke then presented Gen. James Anderson, former State Highway Commissioner, whose paper, entitled, "A Twentieth Century Highway Story", traced the growth of Virginia's highways from its earliest surveys by Justice John Marshall before <date when="1812">1812</date> to the present excellent network serving towns and counties. Gen. Anderson paid special tribute to the efforts of Senator A. Willis Robertson toward improvement of federal highways and to <abbr>Dr.</abbr> Reid White, Judge Stuart Moore, Sen. Robertson and others in the betterment of county roads. The goal set for Rockbridge is a reasonable year-round transportation to accessible and inaccessible places in the County.</p>
<p><abbr>Mrs.</abbr> McCulloch spoke of the passing of Miss Elizabeth Barclay, a long devoted member of the Society, and asked that members observe a moment of silence in her memory.</p>
<p>The Society was honored to have Senator Robertson present for the meeting, as well as <abbr>Mrs.</abbr> John Merritt, a vice-president living away from Lexington.</p>
The address follows:
</front>
<!--TEXT STARTS HERE-->
<body><p>It was with keen regret that I deleted from this paper the story of Virginia's highways for almost the <num type="cardinal" value="300">300</num> years after Jamestown.</p>
<p>Virginia has many firsts in history. The first bridge in the United States was at Jamestown. In <date when="1816">1816</date> Virginia had the first State Department of Public Works. Laommi Baldwin was its first head. A few years later that great man Claudius Crozet came to Virginia as Chief Engineer.</p>
<p>Our state has been fortunate that its leaders for upwards of <num type="cardinal" value="200">200</num> years have realized that Virginia's future depended on the development of its transportation routes. Except for periods of war much of our talents, resources and energy have gone to the improvement of transportation. You and your people have played important parts in developing the highways of Rockbridge and Virginia.</p>
<p>A few years ago I read the biographies of two great Virginians-Marshall's "Life of Washington" and Beveridge's "Life of Marshall." Chief Justice Marshall makes frequent reference to Washington's realization that the development of our nation depended on adequate, safe and economical transportation. Washington urged Virginia to develop its resources by developing transportation routes. Jefferson wrote Washington urging him to lend his name and talents to this development program. Jefferson wrote, "Would the superintendence of this work break in too much on the sweets of retirement and repose. What a monument to your retirement it would be it would remove the only objection."</p>
<p>After John Marshall had been Chief Justice for about ten years he interrupted his on the Supreme Court to take charge of a field
party exploring the most feasible route from the James River near Lynchburg to the Ohio. Beveridge says: "In his <num type="ordinal" value="57">57th</num> year, Marshall set out as head of the expedition and a thorough piece of work he did."Marshall's report is alive with farseeing and statesman like suggestions. It was hard that the War of <date when="1812">1812</date> was getting under way and plans for internal improvements had to be laid aside.</p>
<pb n="97"/>
<p>Canals, turnpikes and railroads were planned and built between the Revolutionary and Civil Wars. Waterways, roads and turnpikes came first, then railroads; in the last fifty years the motor vehicle and the year round road. We’ve never had nearly enough modern roads for our motor vehicles and our use.</p>
<p>My interest in highway development goes back for about 60 years. A few years ago a dear old lady and lifelong friend told a group how she rescued me from the perils of a 1900 highway by taking me up behind her on a high horse. With her help I got to school that day. Without her aid I would have been mired in the cold winter mud and rain for an indefinite period. The roads at the time in my area of Northern Virginia were “6 feet wide and 9 feet deep” – typical rural roads for the United States sixty years ago.</p>
<p>We do not have a great highway system if we have a great arterial system only. We have a great highway system only when we have each mile of road doing the work it should.</p>
<p>In 1901-02 Virginia had its last Constitutional Convention. A scanning of the debates and proceedings of that Convention proved of interest and value. Though improved roads and highways were discussed at length, there is not a paragraph in the Constitution about highways. The consensus at that time, i.e., at the beginning of the 20th Century, was that the improvement of highways was a local problem.</p>
<p>Only four years after the adjournment of the Constitutional Convention the General Assembly in 1906 created the State Highway Commission. Governors Montague and Swanson each had a part in this important work.</p>
<p>The first Commissioner was P. St. Julian Wilson, a V.M.I. graduate of the Class of ‘86, then Assistant Director of Public Works of Richmond. In 1913 he resigned to become Chief Engineer of the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads, Mr. George P. Coleman, who had been serving as assistant was appointed State Highway Commissioner.</p>
<p>For the first few years the Commission aided the Counties with a few widely scattered projects. There was no well planned highway system. The only continuously improved road of any length was the Valley Pike, a toll road, from north to Winchester to Staunton.<p>
<p>The first federal aid highway bill was signed by President Wilson in 1916. Anticipating action on federal aid the Virginia General Assembly set up machinery to provide for a state highway system and a state highway commission. Senators Goolrick, Willis Robertson and Harry Byrd and four from the House including Sinclair Brown made studies and with the help of the Highway Department recommended an initial State Highway System of about 4000 miles. Routes including section 5, what is now U. S. 11 from the West Virginia line via Winchester-Lexington and Roanoke. Also Section 14 from Danville-Lynchburg-Buena Vista-Lexington-Clifton Forge-Covington-West Virginia line with connecting route to Natural Bridge from Balcony Falls and to Eagle Rock from Clifton Forge.</p>
<p>Capt. Wilson as Highway Commissioner had as his early advisors Wm. M. Thornton, Dean of Engineering, University of Virginia; Col. T. A. Jones, Prof. Civil Engineering, V.M.I. and Col. R. A. Marr, Dean of Engineering, V.P.I. After a time Col. Begg replaced Col. Marr. The work of the early Highway Commission was largely advisory. Capt. Wilson listed the following problems in his first report.</p>

The securing of men competent to do permanent road improvement.
Necessary preliminary work in
raising funds
securing proper machinery and equipment
Securing prisoners for service in the State Convict Road Force.
Inadequate provisions for maintenance of roads improved. 

 
<pb n="98"/>
<p>Soon he was to recommend that no county be aided unless suitable provisions for unkeep were made.</p>
<p>Capt. Wilson expressed deep appreciation for the cooperation of the railroads in the state.</p>
<p>Many (maybe I should say most) of the counties had special road laws and Capt. Wilson wanted all counties on a uniform basis.</p>
<p>About this time there was an intensified survey of Virginia's large assortment of road material. Limestone is so plentiful in Rockbridge and of such fine quality that our community has never been short of suitable mateial for road buildings.</p>
<p>West of the Blue Ridge, however, sand for making good Portland Cement concrete is in very poor supply. Hence it is rare to see Portland Cement concrete pavments in our area.</p>
<p>In the first report of the Highway Commission there are listed applications from <num type="cardinal" value="3">3</num> of the <num type="cardinal" value="6">6</num> Districts in Rockbridge-namely Walker's Creek, South River and Natural Bridge. State aid could not be furnished under appropriations available.</p>
<p>In <date when="1907">1907</date> $20,572.54 was spent on roads in Rockbridge. Of this <num type="percentage" value="65">65%</num> was spent by Districts and <num type="percentage" value="35">35%</num> by the County.</p>
<p>The highway commissioner was charged by law with giving equal service, so far as practicable, to each county of the State.</p>
<p>The first salary of the Commissioner was $3,000 per year and his
assistant $1,800.</p>
<p>An engineer appointed by the Commissioner whose salary is not to
exceed $1,200 per year shall be paid by the county having the benefit of his services. Of course the board of supervisors had control over all roads and bridges in the county.</p>
<p>For a long period preceding the Civil War there had been extensive turnpike building. Now the counties are authorized to take over abandoned turnpikes and treat them as other public roads.</p>
<p>In less than two years after the Highway Commission was established <num type="cardinal" value="7">7</num> counties issued bonds for roads.</p>
<table rows="7" cols="2">
<row><cell>Amherst</cell><cell>$80,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Washington</cell><cell>$50,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Russell</cell><cell>$150,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Culpeper</cell><cell>$105,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Orange</cell><cell>$25,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Norfolk</cell><cell>$200,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mecldenburg </cell><cell>$110,000</cell></row>
</table>
<p>While the Commission saw that the people were awake to the importance of building roads they thought it very unwise that proper provision for maintenance was not mandatory.</p>
<p>In <date when="1916">1916</date> came the first Federal Aid Road Act. Among the requirements of the Act were (<num type="cardinal" value="1">1</num>) that a responsible State Highway Department be available to administer the funds and (<num type="cardinal" value="2">2</num>) that a state highway system be established.</p>
<p>With the end of World War I there came an upsurge in the use of motor vehicles. This brought increased demands for year round roads. Senator Willis Robertson had an act passed allowing a community to advance funds for the construction of a certaiin road. This act was used extensively for several years. At one time about 7 million was available from this source.</p>
<pb n="99"/>
<p>There is room for much study and reflection on the changes in our way of life caused by the motor vehicle and the motor road. People who used to think a trip of <num type="cardinal" value="20">20</num> miles was quite an undertaking now think little of a motor trip of thousand miles.</p>
<p><num type="cardinal" value="50">Fifty</num> years ago in Lexington it was easy to tell which boys and girls came from town and which from the country. Now these differences have been effectively wiped out.</p>
<p>In <date when="1922">1922</date> Virginia secured the services of one of the ablest highway administrators in the United States. Henry G. Shirley, who was born in West Virginia and educated at <choice><expan>Virginia Military Institute</expan><abbr>V.M.I</abbr></choice>, had extensive railroad and highway experience when he assumed his duties as Chairman of the Virginia Highway Commission. A gentleman of great force he proved to be one of the finest public servants Virginia has ever had. Under his management the state highway system rapidly took shape and meaning.</p>
<p>In <date when="1923">1923</date> it was decided in a state-wide reforendum that Virginia would build its roads in a "pay-as-you-go" plan and not by bond issues.This proved a very wise decision for our roads benefited by increased knowledge of highway traffic and increased knowledge of the evolution of the motor vehicle and highway design.</p>
<p>In <date when="1932">1932</date> under the stress of the depression the Byrd Road Law was passed. This placed the County Roads of <num type="cardinal" value="96">96</num> of Virginia's <num type="cardinal" value="100">100</num> counties under the State Highway Department. <num type="cardinal" value="4">Four</num> counties voted to look after their own roads but one of the <num type="cardinal" value="4">four</num> came along with the <num type="cardinal" value="96">96</num> after one year.</p>
<p>The provisions of the Act were wisely drawn. In effect it set up a partnership the Boards of Supervisors and the Highway Department. Public hearings are held by the Board of Supervisors on the Secondary Highway Budget. Keeping county officials and interested citizens close to local road picture has proved extremely helpful. The partnership arrangement has proved most rewarding.</p>
<p>The Highway Commission must of necessity have broad powers in
the location of roads, allocation of funds, etc. The General Assembly provided that the Commission divide the state into not less than <num type="cardinal" value="8">8</num> construction districts and called on the Commission to make an equitable distribution of funds among the Districts. Public hearings must be held on fund allocations before they can be made final. Many of you have attended these hearings.</p>
<p>As we all know population centers create traffic as well as costly problems of highway construction and maintenance. Almost everyone is a traffic expect and a highway engineer. This universal interest in what is being done helps keep the public informed.</p>
<p>The world boom in highway transportation that we are experiencing builds world wealth and revolutionizes our economic outlook. We look forward confidently toward an era of better living. We see no end to progress.</p>
<p>Quick transportation has opened the markets of the world to all. Improvement in transportation is one of the powerful forces for the uplift of man.</p>
<p>In all phases of highway work brains are in demand. We need better educated and better trained men at every level. The whole world is moving in the direction of better, safer highways.</p>
<p>Take a look to the future and forecast if you dare the traffic, the population, the wealth and standard of living in the years ahead.</p>
<p>It has been determined beyond doubt that the same routes which best serve our peace time economy serve the nation best in time of war or other emergency.</p>
<p>Ploughing back <num type="cardinal" value="100">$100</num> million plus and more a year for the good of all Virginians is a real challenge and a splendid opportunity. Our problems will best be solved by able, devoted, talented career men who find life's richest rewards in service for Virginia.</p>
<p>A few years ago the Department of Highways celebrated its 50th or Golden Anniversary. Our friends told us that while we had made a start it was but a start. They predicted and I'm sure they are right,
<pb n="100"/>
that must do more work in the next <num type="cardinal" value="15">15</num> years than we did the first fifty.</p>
<p>Right here I'd like to pause to pay tribute to the citizens of Lexington, Buena Vista and Rockbridge County for their work for highway development. Among those taking a prominent part we may name-</p>
<p>Capt. Corsie, <abbr>Dr.</abbr> Reid White, Capt. Letcher, Rice Hotinger, Frank Moore, Willis Robertson, Stuart Moore, C. S. Glasgow and many others.</p>
<p>In <date when="1922">1922</date> the Town Council decided it was time to try to satisfy demands for street improvement. Estimates were prepared and the citizens voted a bond issue for <num type="cardinal" value="85,000">$85,000</num>. This was spent for curb and gutter and pavements and I believe proved a very worthwhile investment. Many problems are now apparent that could not be foreseen <num type="cardinal" value="38">38</num> years ago. If we planned improvements today standards would be entiriely different.</p>
<p>In <date when="1925">1925</date> a by-pass for Lexington was suggested. In 1955-30 years later a by-pass for U.S. 11 was opened to traffic. It very properly took time, study and meditation to decide on the coursie to be taken, but 30 years is a long time in the 20th Century.</p>
<p>In order to make maps, put up signs, keep accounts and the like it is necessary that each section of highway have a positve means of identification. About 35 years ago in order to aid interstate travel the National State Highway Officials Association set up a U.S. numbered system of highways. Odd numbered routes run North and South, even numbered routes East and West. Roads of special significance end in 1 for North-South and 0 for East-West. Thus Lexington is fortunate in having two primary transcontinental Route 3, U.S. 11 and U.S. 60 crossing here. Few places in Virginia are so fortunate. The U.S. shield with the state name was adopted for convenience and does not mean that the Federal Government has either special interest or special funds in the Route. Though the U.S. Numbered System has been in effect for more than 30 years it is hard for us to realize that the Federal Government has nothing to do with it.</p>
<p>In Virginia all Primary Routes are numbered under 600. Thus in Rockbridge we have 11, 60, 501, 39, 251, 130, etc. as Primary Routes. All secondary or county roads begin with the number 600 and go as high as needed.</p>
<p>One of the facts that is becoming apparent is that we no longer need great centers of population or metropolitan areas even for heavy industry. Workers can live within one hundred miles of the plant they serve and go back and forth each day with a proper net of year round roads.The 41,000 miles of arterial roads is properly known as the Interstate and Defense Highway System. When you can go from Boston to Seattle without a traffic light on a highway 3 to 5 times as safe as the ordinary arterial, progress is being made.</p>
<p>In the last few years under the Revenue Bond Act of 1940 and other acts Virginia has expended or will expend over $300 million for Bridge and Tunnel projects. The Highway Department sold $95 million to finance the Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel and other projects. The Elizabeth River Tunnel Commission soon will have 2 tunnels connecting Norfolk and Portsmouth. Cost more than $40 million.</p>
<p>The Chesapeake Bay Bridge and Tunnel is a 17 1/2 mile long project, expected to cost upwards of $200 million and be ready for service in 3 years. The Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike is a $70 million bottle-neck breaker from North Richmond to South of Petersburg. Motor vehicle registrations are up 3% in the last year. Total number 1,400,000.</p>
<p>The 7 cents gas tax produces about 85% of the state highway revenue.</p>
<p>Motor vehicle fees 12% and other fees 3%-total over $100 million a year.</p>
<p>Our people-particularly rural residents-are so on the
motor vehicle and the year round road that only a few days stoppage of service could cause much hardship. About 1900 there were counted 300 slieighs in Harrisonburg on a court day. 50 years later there was only one sleigh in the city and that was a museum piece. We are happy Highway Department has a force of trained workers who can be used for relief and reserve wherever and whenever necessary.</p>
<pb n="101"/>
<p>Village roads and streets are part of the county system in which they are located, but incorporated towns and cities doing their own street work receive very substantial aid from highway funds. While there is never enough money to satisfy reasonable demands, it is true that each kind of road receives attention.</p>
<p>Allocations to Rockbridge County's secondary roads for '60-'61 total $507,985. When the county were taken over in <date when="1932">1932</date> less than 5% were hard surfaced. Now over 200 miles are hard-surfaced or more than 35%. Over 40% more have an all weather surface, so more than 75% are year round roads. Less than 25% are light surfaced, less than 1% unsurfaced.</p>
<p>One of the fine things the ladies clubs of Virginia can take credit for is the establishment of a landscape division under a competent landscape engineer. This division improves and beautifies the roadside while improving drainage and promoting conservation.</p>
<p>Please take a good look at the change in the economic life of most communities under 1500 population. People shop in larger towns for most of the necessities of life. Yet these smaller communities are served by motor cars, trucks and buses as they never could have been served by railroads.</p>
<p>As economic development is accelerated higher standards of living prevail.</p>
<p>It is probable that if we set up a goal for Rockbridge roads it would read something like this "A reasonably adequate year round road to every reasonably located farm and rural dwelling in Rockbridge."</p>
<p>Some day our goal will be reached.</p>
<pb n="102"/>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
