<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
  <titleStmt>
   <title>
         Buckle Down Winsocki: Washington and Lee during World War II
   </title>
   <author> I. Taylor Sanders II</author>
   <editor> Larry I. Bland </editor>
   <sponsor> Rockbridge Historical Society </sponsor>
   <respStmt>
      <resp> Encoding by: </resp><name>
      Michael Schoenberg '27</name>
   </respStmt>
  </titleStmt>
  <editionStmt>

  </editionStmt>
  <extent>
      extent of digital XML file
  </extent>
  <publicationStmt>
   <publisher>Rockbridge Historical Society</publisher>
   <distributer>Rockbridge Historical Society</distributer>
   <distributer> Washington and Lee University</distributer>
   <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
   <date>2003</date>
   <idno type="ISSN">0080-3383</idno>
   <availability> 
      <p> Proceedings of the Rockbridge Historical Society, Volume 12.
Copyright @ 2003</p>
</availability>
  </publicationStmt>
  <seriesStmt>
   <title> Proceedings of the Rockbridge Historical Society</title>
</seriesStmt>
  <noteStmt> 
   <note> Text encoded as part of DCI 295D: Digital Editions, Fall 2023</note>

  </noteStmt>
  <notesStmt>
   <note>
<!-- notes on other aspects of the resource -->
   </note>
  </notesStmt>
  <sourceDesc>

  </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
 <body> 
  <pb n="1"/>DURING that fall term <date when="1939">1939</date>, <placeName id="WLU">>Washington and Lee</placeName> men were not
oblivious to the news that <placeName id="EURO">Europe</placeName> and <placeName id="ASIA">Asia</placeName> were tearing them-
selves apart. In fact, they followed international developments
closely. The faculty, some of whom remembered <date when="1914">1914</date>, made a
special effort, particularly in history courses, to keep their pupils abreast
of the world scene. That autumn saw frequent comments in class on con-
temporary politics and an expanded series of guest lectures on campus.
Most notably, in <date when="1939">October 1939</date>, a German sociologist appeared in <placeName id="#LEX1">Lex-
ington</placeName> to offer his view on the <org>Nazi movement</org>. Student writers in the
<org>Ring-tum-Phi</org> stressed international affairs. For example, <persName>Bill "Buck"
Buchanan</persName>, later a politics professor at <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>, wrote a
series on the "Conflagration in Europe."<div>
When the freshmen graduated four years later in <date when="1943">1943</date>, they
regarded themselves as the <q>"class that never saw <placeName>W and L</placeName> as it was in a
world at peace."</q> Despite the shadow of war, the patterns of college life
carried on in traditional ways, and the late <date when="1930s">1930s</date> had been good ones
for <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>. By <date when="1939">1939</date>, thanks largely to defense spending,
the country began to muscle its way out of the depression. For <placeName>W and L</placeName> this
translated into a larger number of well-qualified applicants-perhaps the
best prepared in its history. Several major gifts, including the Doremus
legacy, helped the school assume a sounder financial footing.</div>
<div> 
<pb n="2"/> </div>
<div>
   The nineteen social fraternities continued to serve new Minks.
Freshmen soon learned that if they wanted to eat, they better pledge a
house quickly. Literary societies, debate, publications, and the presti-
gious <org>Cotillion Club</org> flourished. For that gregarious young generation
with its optimistic, can-do spirit, new clubs continued to emerge, such as
the new <org>pre-med society</org>. Organizations, new and old, simply added a
counterpoint to the rhythm of traditional campus life of fall weekends,
football, and classes, with the famed <placeName>W and L</placeName> convertible fleet convoying
hordes of Minks down the road to neighboring women's colleges. And
that year, 205 of 281 freshmen pledged one of the fraternities on campus.
</div>
<div>
   As was often the case in the school's history, prospects for the foot-
ball team were gloomy. Spirits rose with our defeat of <placeName id="WVU">West Virginia</placeName> and
with a freshman team <org>(the Brigadiers)</org> who, for the first time in our his-
tory, actually defeated powerful <placeName id="UM">Maryland</placeName>. That <date when="October">October</date> nearly 350
women (then called "girls") invaded the campus for the Opening Ball,
and <persName>Cy Young</persName> resigned as basketball coach to be replaced by a man
from <placeName>Ohio State University</placeName>. 
</div>
<div> At the <placeName>State Theater</placeName> students joined with <persName Lew Ayers</persname> and <persName>Lionel Bar-
rymore</persName> to learn the <title>Secret of Dr Kildare</title>, and they laughed with the <org>Marx
Brothers</org> At The Circus. By the new year, students had tapped <persName>Kay Kyser</persName>
to play for the Fancy Dress Ball, set the advance ticket costs at $9.50, and
selected a <placeName>Kentucky</placeName> Derby theme. The college told hopeful parents to
expect to spend a total of some $7OO per academic year to educate their
sons comfortably at <placeName>W and L</placeName>. </div>
<div>Perhaps the biggest flap that fall came on <date when="1939-26-09">September 26, 1939</date>, three
weeks after the European democracies declared war on <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and
as the <org>Nazis</org> were mopping up after their Polish blitzkrieg, when the edi-
tor of the <org><choice><abbr>Phi</abbr><expan>Ring-Tum-Phi</expan><org> attacked the <placeName>Washington and Lee<placeName> Swing as being <q>"clumsy,
often pointless and inane."<q></div>
<div><persName>John Graham</persName>, the professor who had composed the song years
before, was hurt when confronted with the criticism of his old tune. Yet
he had to agree with the editor's aesthetic judgment. He noted, however,
that he could not see the alumni agreeing with a change in the school
song. The next week the <org>student newspaper</org> reported support for <persName>Gra-
ham</persName> and the song with banner headlines: <q>"LEAVE THE SWING
ALONE"</q> and announced that the presidents of the <org>E.C.</org> and <org>Omicron
Delta Kappa service organization</org> stronely suoported the "Swing."</div>
<div>Normal college life went on unabated during <date>1939</date> and into <date>1940</date>,
broken only by a two-month long epidemic of robberies in fraternity
houses, the long-awaited appearance of the film <title>Gone With The Wind</title>,
which blew into town, as students said, on <date when="11-03">March 11</date>, and the eighth con-
secutive Mock Political Convention. <persName>Graham was thrilled when the <date>1940</date>
<org>Glee Club</org> became nationally known with a series of victories in singing</div> 
<div>
<pb n="2"/> </div>
<div>competition; and a raucous mock convention followed in <date when="1940-10">October 1940</date>
when <placeName>W and L</placeName> students overwhelmingly supported <persName>Wendell Willkie</persName> for
president in a straw poll. But the big news in the fall of <date>1940</date> was that
<persName>Benny Goodman</persName>, who was unable to play for the Opening Ball because
of illness, had agreed to play at Fancy Dress during the spring of <date>1941</date>'</div>
<div>
   The <org><mascot>Generals</mascot></org> won only two football games in the fall of <date>1940</date>, with
seven losses and a tie, but the game films convinced most Minks that the
officials had cheated the Blues out of one crucial touchdown. The wider
world of defense policy and big-time sports intruded the next spring,
when <placeName>W and L</placeName> decided to establish a compulsory <org>Reserve Officers Tiaining
Corps unit</org>, and noted tennis champion <persName>Fred Perry</persName> agreed to coach at
<placeName>W and L</placeName>.</div>
<div>In <date when="1941-09"> September 1941</date>, the school broke all previous attendance records
as 486 new students enrolled at the college. A campus poll the next
month reported that 30 percent of 803 students still preferred to stay out
of the war. This paralleled a national Gallup survey showing that some
70 percent of the American public favored a German defeat. Thirteen
students registered no opinion on the matter. Events in the <placeName>Pacific</placeName> would
change that.</div>
<div>By early <date when="1941-12">December 1941</date>, <persName>Woody Herman</persName> had just signed on for
Fancy Dress, when the news of <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName> shocked the campus. (In
the <date when="1941-09-12">December 9</date> <org> Ring-tum-Phi</org>, <persName>Herman</persName> got a 60-point, four-column
headline. The news of Pearl Harbor got a 3O-point, two-column head-
line.) Social scientists like to talk about defining social moments, those
shocks that radically alter people's social or cultural environment-that
sort of event where years later one remembers exactly where and how
the news arrived. That Sunday in <date>December 1941</date> was such a moment-
and it became the defining event for an entire generation.</div>
<div>
   On that quiet Sunday afternoon, students were preparing for jaunts
to the women's colleges. More studious boys, known as <soCalled>"crammers"</soCalled> or
members of the <soCalled>"sunday afternoon library study team,"</soCalled> headed for
<placeName>McCormick Library</placeName>. Rumors of <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName> swept the campus' and
soon students had dropped their books, parked their cars, and gathered
around radios. Road trips were cancelled. Bull sessions replaced dates as
the war, which most students had been expecting, finally arrived. Rather
than being immediately galvanized, however, the atmosphere on cam-
pus was one of uncertainty as students pondered the fate of the five fel-
low Minks who had been drafted since <date>September</date>.</div>
<div>The next day, <date>Monday</date>, students chècked their mail boxes and
called local draft boards. One group, after stopping off at the post office,
went across the street to the <placeName>Corner Grill</placeName>, sat down at tables, and quietly
reviewed their situation. Coins poured into the juke box and over and
over again they played the popular song, <title>Buckle Down Winsocki</title>. By the
<pb n="4"/> </div>
<div>
   next day, <date>Tuesday</date>, uncertainty gave way to a new feeling, one of <soCalled>"cool-
ness and determination,"</soCalled> and the spirit on campus was <q>"Buckle Down."</q></div>
<div>The entire <date>1942</date> winter semester reflected that spirit, and advertising
in the <org>Ring-tum-Phi</org> took on a military flavor. To save gasoline and wear
on tires, road trips ended. To avoid flunking out under the automatic
rule, which would lead to an immediate draft, students buckled down to
their studies. They did this so that they would have some choice as to
how they would spend the war. Others signed up for classes in civilian
pilot training. All realized that their lives had been changed. </div>
<div> Many members of the class of 1942 look back upon <persName>Dr. Francis
Pendleton Gaines</persName>'s presidential farewell to them at graduation as the
most moving moment of their days in <placeName>Lexington</placeName>. <persName>Dr. Gaines</persName> pointed out
to them that they were going into a world that they could <q>"not even
imagine on that huppy day when you first invested your capacities for
learning and development into the safekeeping of <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>.
. . . Muy God bless you and be with you. I should make that prayer for
any graduating class, but I assure you that I have in my heart a peculiar
sincerity as I utter the words in your behalf."</q></div>
<div>He continued to speak, telling them that the task facing them was</div>
<div> <q>greater . . . than any outgoing class has known for many years. I hope
you will believe it is a worthy task. It is my confidence that because of
your wisdom and your character you will not spend idle hours in
remorse that an older generation brought the world to an unhappy sit-
uation which you must straighten out. I am sure that because of your
faith you will not dishonor yourself by a kind of fatalism in which you
say you have just run into bad luck.</div>
<div>
On the contrary, I have an assurance that you will know, whatever
be the personal sacrifice, that it is your privilege, really and truly, to
make a better world. Let me urge that you keep steadfast in your heart
a strong purpose for the fulfillment of your own personal dreams, and
that whenever this interruption shall cease you will take up again the
energetic fulfillment of the plan by which you may live most happily
and most usefully. In the meantime, however, as I leave on record this
farewell, I remind you that it is a great thing you set forth to do, and I
know you will do your part.</q></div>
<div>
   Official government policy wisely urged college students to stay in
school for the time being. This helped a number of colleges that other-
wise might have collapsed to survive the first months of crisis. As late as
<date>1943</date>, federal policy was that students should not immediately rush to
the colors; rather, they should remain on campus where they could
<q>"develop qualities of leadership."</q> Colleges and universities were urged
to <q>"provide effective education to meet the needs of technical, scientific,
and other professional services."</q> All this was easier said than done.</div>
<div>
<pb n="5"/> </div>
<div>
<placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName> altered the atmosphere of typical college life swiftly
and forever, but structural change came slower and worked itself out
during early <date>1942</date>. At their <date>February</date> meeting, trustees approved a sum-
mer session to accelerate graduation, and for the first time in the school's
history allowed women to study here during the summer of <date>1942</date>. This
news made a splash in the press when an <org>Associated Press</org> story was fea-
tured in the <org>Memphis Commercial Appeal</org> with a headline: <q>"W and L Goes
Sissy."</q></div>
<div>
   Some 286 summer students enrolled in <date when="1942-06">June 1942</date>; twenty-four were
women. By the fall of <date>1942</date>, 1B7 students had enlisted. By year's end,
fourteen alumni had been killed in action, most from the classes of <date>1939</date>
through <date>1942</date>. We began the <date>1942</date>-<date><abbr>43</abbr><expand>1943</expand></date> academic year with some 300
fewer students than the normal 900. By the end of the year, we had only
300 students left. Needless to say, campus social life was strictly cur-
tailed.</div>
<div>In <date when="1942-12">December 1942</date>, the trustees cancelled football for the duration,
and within three months the <org>Ring-tum-Phi</org> suspended publication until
the war ended. Instead of name bands, local groups played for student
dances. Flowers on corsages were replaced by war savings stamps. By
that spring the president of the spring dance set had joined up. So had
all but one of the junior class officers, and the yearbook that year was a
tribute to the more than eighteen hundred alumni who were engaged in
the struggle.</div>
<div>Graduation <date>1943</date> is still etched in that class's memory. The class had
been hard hit by attrition and the accelerated academic program. When
the new graduates gathered in front of <placeName><persName>Lee</persName> Chapel</placeName> at sunrise after grad-
uation to sing "College Friendships," it was an emotional scene. More-
over, the administrators were facing a prospect of fewer than one
hundred students enrolling for the fall term.</div>
<div> 
   <persName>Dr. Gaines</persName> could not afford to remain emotional for long. He faced
a crisis. As with many American colleges of the time, we confronted pos-
sible extinction. Gaines worked overtime to get some sort of govern-
ment program here and, aided apparently by <orgname>Army</orgname> Chief of Staff
<persName>General George C. Marshall</persName>, a <placeName><abbr>VMI</abbr><expand>Virginia Military Institute</expand></placeName> graduate who had fond memories
of <placeName>Lexington</placeName>, the president succeeded. The program at <placeName>W and L</placeName>, together
with the influx of GIs enrolled in the <org>Army Specialized taining Pro-
gram</org> <abbr>(ASTP)</abbr> at <placeName><abbr>VMI</abbr><expand>Virginia Military Institute</expand></placeName>, changed the town. One of the participants at
<placeName><abbr>VMI</abbr><expand>Virginia Military Institute</expand></placeName>, <persName>Gore Vidal</persName>, who later won fame as a writer, studied with <persName>Colonel
Carrington Tutwiler</persName>. Another ersatz <abbr>ASTP</abbr> Keydet was the comedian
<persName>Mel Brooks</persName>. When asked years later what he had done during the war,
<persName>Mel</persName> responded with zeal: <q>"I went to Virginia Military Institute and
learned to become a Confederate cavalry officer."</q> </div> 
<div> 
   <pb n="6"/> </div>
<img> Gotta figure out how to get that in here </img>
<div>
<pb n="7"/> </div>
<div> 
During much of <date>1942</date>, <persName>Gaines</persName>, who was always an effective sales-
man, lobbied the <org>Army</org> to establish some sort of program on campus.
He urged the military to consider what an ideal place this campus was
for the Army. Classroom space, available faculty, indeed' the whole
atmosphere of a college is aimed, as he said, at pushing students to cover
<q>"swiftly a large program of intensive study."</q> Lexington was the perfect
place. Its two colleges had the classrooms-the government would not
have to build them. The Army could have full use of the library, gym,
swimming pools, tennis courts, and lab space. Furthermore, <placeName>Lexington</placeName>
had medical facilities in place.</div>
<div> 
   His case, presented during <date>1942</date> and later when it looked as if the
school might move, struck a chord. We signed a contract in mid-<date>1942</date>
that insured <placeName>W and L</placeName>'s survival. Thus, <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName> welcomed the
<org>School for Special and Morale Services</org>. The official purpose of the
School, which had been located at <placeName>Fort Meade, Maryland</placeName>, was to devise,
plan, and supervise <q>"practicable activities for combat troops in Theaters
of Operations domestic and overseas,"</q> and to <q>"instruct and train <org>Army</org>
personnel in the approved purposes, doctrines, materials, methods and
operative procedures in all phases of the duties and responsibilities of
the Special Services Branch."</q> That branch consisted of combat officers
who would command units close to the lines and deliver recreation,
games, movies, reviews, shows, and other morale support for the fight-
ing men.</div>
<div>
   A special propaganda room in the library supported that part of the
program aimed at training officers to answer questions that might arise
àmong front line troops: What are we doing here? Why are we fighting?
why is <persName>Hitler</persName> so dangerous? Is this really my war?</div>
<div>the administration made a rental arrangement with the <org>Army</org>, leas-
ing virtually the entire campus to the military. We charged the govern-
ment 99 cents per day for each person living on campus and 49 cents for
each soldier living off campus. In <date when="1942-11">November 1942</date>, we advised the fresh-
men that they would have to vacate <placeName>Graham-Lees dormitory</placeName> by 6 P.M.
on <date when="28-11">November 28</date>. Students moved their clothes and baggage into private
homes as the troops moved into the dorm. <persName>President Gaines</persName> advised his
students that this arrangement might save the freshmen as much as four
dollars per month. Classes at the Army school began on <date when="1942-12-7">December 7</date>,
one year to the day after <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName>.</div>
<div>Other than the construction of <placeName>Washington Annex</placeName> behind <placeName>Washing-
ton Hall</placeName>, which served as the enlisted men's mess hall, the <org>Army</org> used
regular campus facilities. <placeName>Tucker Hall</placeName> and <placeName>Robinson Hall</placeName> became the
headquarters. The finance section moved into <placeName>Newcomb Hall</placeName>. <placeName>Reid Hall</placeName>
was used for classroom space and a lounge. Dormitories served as bar-
racks, a PX, and an officer's mess. A home on Letcher Avenue became</div>
<div> 
   <pb n="8"/> </div>
   <img> insert image here </img>
</div>

<div> 
   <org>The Officer's Club</org>, and the motor pool was established below the gym
at the corner of <placeName><persName>Washington</persName></placeName> and <placeName><persName>Nelson Streets</persName></placeName>. The college and the
school shared <placeName>McCormick Library</placeName>, which also housed, under armed
guard, a moving van's worth of valuable documents from the <org>U.S.
National Archives</org>. <placeName>Washington Hall</placeName> was the focus for normal college
activities.</div>
<div> Many members of the faculty had already left to join the war effort.
Others who remained threw themselves into the work of the <org>Army
School</org>. <persName>Dean Frank Gilliam</persName> was the first liaison officer. <persName>Rupert Latture</persName></div>
<div> 
   <pb n="9"/> </div>

   <div> stepped in to become <placeName>W and L</placeName>'s Dean of Students, Director of Housing, and
Buildings and Grounds Director. <persName>Dr. Allen Moger</persName> became Director of
Testing at the <org>Army School</org>.</div>
<div> 
   Initially, the personnel included 20 civilians, 60 enlisted men, and
90 officers. At its peak it employed 125 civilians, 100 enlisted men, and
90 officers. Over the weeks, quirks smoothed out and difficulties eased,
and by early <date>1944</date>, the <org>School for Special Services</org> was running full tilt.
Some twelve hundred young officer trainees moved through the pro-
gram swiftly, in twenty-eight days, completing some 192 hours of
instruction.</div>
<div> 
   They learned to run a PX, produce variety shows, organize games,
and conduct physical training. Each Sunday evening they presented
matinees at <placeName>Doremus Gym</placeName> for local crowds of productions like <title>USA, OK</title>
or <title>Hi, Yank</title>. Among the participants were <persName>David Wayne</persName>, who presented
<placeName>Broadway</placeName>-level shows, and <persName>Red Skelton</persName>, who kept <placeName><persName>Lexingtonians</persName></placeName>
rolling in the aisles long before he became a famous television comic.
<persName>Melvin Douglas</persName> and <persName>Lanny Ross</persName> thrilled townsfolk with their talents.
One instructor, <persName>Norm Lord</persName>, grew to love this place so much, he decided
to live here after the war.</div>
<div>
   Although the School provided some of the best entertainment <placeName>Lex-
ington</placeName> has ever enjoyed, its aim was deadly serious. Trainees learned to
relieve troops of boredom, and keep combat soldiers happy, in touch
with their families, and informed of war aims and news in a way that
countered the <org>Axis war       (image over here learn how to get that in)
machine</org>'s propaganda.
Although the program was
strictly military, the atmos-
phere was open. <placeName><persName>Lexingto-
nians</persName></placeName> enjoyed the concerts,
shows, and symposiums,
and many local people par-
ticipated in the programs,
which in time expanded to
several sections dealing
with recreation, orienta-
tion, education, and per-
sonnel services, training
officers to draw up wills,
handle insurance issues,
and even ameliorate family
disputes. In time, the pro-
gram's increased scope
required quartering three</div>
<div>
<pb n="10"/> </div>

<div>
   or four troopers per dorm room, and the basement of <placeName>Lee Chapel</placeName> was
used as a lecture hall eight hours each day.</div>
<div>Some years ago, one student, <persName>Will Tankersley</persName>, wrote an excellent
essay on the program, in which he discussed <persName>Dr. Moger</persName>'s testing meth-
ods. <persName>Dr. Moger</persName>, for many years professor of history at <placeName>Washington and
Lee </placeName>and a prime mover in the <org>Rockbridge Historical Society</org>, ran a test-
ing program that was both rigorous and humane. Students took up to
four exams during the course. But the need for personnel was so crucial
that some men who failed the tests eventually graduated from the pro-
gram, especially if they had talent. <persName>Dr. Moger</persName> reported that <persName>Red Skelton</persName>,
for example, who never rose above the rank of private because he was
happy where he was, <q>"couldn't pass any exam devised by the mind of
man."</q> He was certified, however, because of his show business skills.</div>
<div> During this period, <persName>Dr. Gaines</persName>'s task was not easy and his job no
laughing matter. In addition to trying to keep his now very small college
afloat and traveling around the country using his oratorical skills in the
War Bond effort, he found himself constantly having to stroke the <org>Army</org>
in order to keep it here. His job was made more difficult by some of our
alumni and by the widespread racial prejudice that marked them and
plagued that era.</div>
<div> 
   Some of our <soCalled>"old grads"</soCalled> grew concerned when they heard that black
troops were being trained at <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>. One of them was a
<org>Virginia newspaper</org> editor who, in the words of another alumnus who
strongly supported <persName>Gaines</persName>, was quite <q>"rabid"</q> on the race issue. The mat-
ter vexed the president, especially between <date>March</date> and <date>November</date> <date>1943</date>.
In <date>March</date>, African-American newspapers around the country published
a story that four Negroes would receive diplomas in <placeName>Lee Chapel</placeName>. The
story said that <q>"history will be made Saturday when, for the first time,
four Negroes-the first ever to attend a major Vhite College in the
South"-will graduate. The paper reported that the men "have been
attending the old Virginia College and living on campus, along with
white officers.</q></div>
<div>Stories like this continued to surface, and, by <date>November</date>, an <placeName>Atlanta</placeName>
alumnus wrote <persName>Gaines</persName>, informing him that <q>"loose talk is going around"</q>
town that colored girls were attending dances at the college and that
blacks and whites were dancing together in <placeName>Lexington</placeName>. Some of the let-
ters were insulting, sharply worded, and, looking back on them now,
totally inappropriate, if not pig-headed. They also nearly cost <placeName>W and L</placeName> the
<org>Army School</org>. At least one alumnus stepped over the bounds when he
protested to <placeName><persName>Washington</persName></placeName> about the presence of black students on cam-
pus. The general in charge of the program informed <persName>Gaines</persName> that unless
he muzzled the protesters, the government would cancel the contract.
The <org>Army school</org> would be transferred to <placeName>Washington State University</placeName></div>
<div> 
   <pb n="11"/> </div>

   <div>
      <persName>Gaines</persName>, whose skill as a letter writer matched his talents as an ora-
tor, took on the protesters. His letters developed consistent themes.
After smoothing any ruffled feathers, he pointed out that the university
was renting out its campus to a government school and that W and L had
no choice as to who attended the program, nor did the school control its
content. Then he carefully stressed that no <placeName><persName>Lexingtonians</persName></placeName>-and they knew the program best-had voiced criticism.</div>
<div>Then he pulled up his howitzers. He reminded the alumni that the
country was in a national emergency. He informed them that <q>"Negroes
as well as Whites"</q> are offering their lives in the nation's service. He
explained that ours was the only school in the country that offered such
a program, the aims of which he carefully explained. He stressed that
<q>"Negro units in our fighting forces need the same kind of morale lead-
ership in the hands of trained specialists that white forces need. He said
that numbers of African Americans in <placeName>Lexington</placeName> were small, but he also
stressed that they "have to get this training at our school or those Negro
units would not get that type of leadership."</q> <persName>Gaines</persName>, who knew the South
and its problems as well as anyone, was always informative, honest, and
firm. And in time the issue died down.</div>
<div> 
   To appreciate the pressures he faced, remember that during this
period, through the summer and into the autumn of <date>1943</date>, <persName>Gaines</persName> was
<soCalled>"drafted,"</soCalled> as he said, to chair the <org>Virginia War Bonds program</org>. He wrote
that the scope of the program, which was <q>"to raise the biggest amount of
money in history"</q> caused him <q>"one uninterrupted headache."</q> When he
took over the effort during the summer, he found that the two agencies
in charge-the <org>War Savings Staff</org> and the <org>Victory Loan Committee</org> for
special drives-were being merged and the combined operation was in
an <q>"incredible mess."</q> The task meant frequent trips to <placeName>Richmond</placeName> and
<placeName>Washington</placeName>, and culminated in a massive war bonds campaign that
began on <date when="1943-20-09">September 20, 1943</date>.</div>
<div>During this same period, <persName>Gaines</persName> coped with running his university.
One student asserted that <placeName>W and L</placeName> had <q>"lost a greater percentage of her stu-
dent body to the armed forces than any other college."</q> Summing up, he
said: <q>"Everything changed, everything was halved, quartered, or ruled
out. Things which had mattered no longer did." He believed that W and L
was of all schools "hardest hit by the war."</q></div>
<div>
   The number of students attending <placeName>W and L</placeName> during the war seems
incredibly small by today's standards. From <date>February</date> to <date>August</date> <date>1945</date>,
we awarded a grand total of eight degrees. The administration's rule of
thumb seemed to be that the school would remain open so long as there
were one hundred students in attendance. The typical freshman class
then numbered some forty boys. The curriculum had to be adjusted and
efforts made to offer a full freshman and sophomore program in the <org>col-</div>

<div>
   <pb n="12"/> </div>



<div> lege and Commerce School</org> from <date>1943</date> to <date>1945</date>. Recruitment material
stressed that high school graduates at sixteen or seventeen could make
their <q>"wisest investment"</q> by attending <placeName>W and L</placeName> between the time they com-
pleted high school and reached the selective service age of eighteen.</div>
<div>All upper level programs-pre-med, pre-engineering, and journal-
ism-depended on demand. In his messages to the students, many of
whom were seventeen-year-olds who had completed high school and
were waiting to be called, <persName>Gaines</persName> stressed <q>those things which had stayed
the same: our traditions of warmth and friendliness, our emphasis on the
individual, the core of our spiritual heritage, and honor. These still mat-
tered. All else had, indeed, changed.</q></div>
<div> 
   In <date>December</date> <date>1942</date>, the trustees captured the school's spirit when
they voted to discontinue intercollegiate sports <q>"until the war is won . . .
thus abandoning the battles of the playing field for the greater fight."</q>
Great stress was placed on intramurals and physical education. Running
an obstacle course became a major pastime for the boys whose big
brothers, only months before, had been running down the road.</div>
<div> 
   A few students were disappointed by the cutbacks, particularly the
drastically reduced social life, lack of big name bands, and curtailed
graduation ceremonies. One student used the school newspaper to
lament the changes. He insisted that since <q>"he and his classmates faced
uncertain futures and were in the last year of school, they ought to go
out in style with gay dances, caps and gowns . . . and the rest of the
things that make up <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>."</q></div>
<div>The case of one fraternity, <org>the Betas</org>, gives the period flavor. On
<date when="1942-08-05">May 8, 1943</date>, <org>Alpha Rho chapter of Beta Theta Pi</org> had its last meeting
and passed out of existence when virtually all the members entered the
service. After graduation, a handful of brothers remained behind to
close down the house. They stored all chapter records, books, and tro-
phies at a local bank, and loaned out the furniture to <placeName>Lexington</placeName> homes
for safekeeping. The end of an era arrived when the remaining brother
turned over the house key to the <org>University Registrar</org>. Two members
remained behind for the summer session, but when the last brother
graduated and joined the <org>Navy</org>, the chapter was gone. <placeName>Red Square</placeName>
joined other campus facilities that were tumed over to the <org>Army</org> for use
by <org>the School of Special Services</org></div>
<div> 
   During the closing months of the war, <placeName>W and L</placeName> began sending out bul-
letins urging young Americans to consider their <q>"post-war education"</q> at
<placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>. In time, <persName>President Gaines</persName>could report that about
one-third of the school's living alumni and one-half of the staff were
either in uniform or engaged in war work. Among the alumni, 136 were
lost in the war.</div>
<div>
   <pb n="13"/> </div>

   <div>
      During the summer of <date>1945</date>, <placeName>W and L</placeName> began to receive inquiries from
former faculty members about jobs at postwar <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>, and
we began to gear up for our largest enrollments in history. But <persName>Dr.
Gaines</persName>, ever mindful of the budget, urged all former professors to stay
in uniform as long as they could.</div>
<div>
   It is remarkable how quickly the school got back to normal after
World War II. Quick demobilization, spurred on by the <soCalled>"Bring Daddy
Home by Christmas"</soCalled> campaign, led to a rapid decline in the number of
students at the <org>Special Services program</org>. On <date when="1946-06-06">June 6, 1946</date>, the <org>Army</org>
School pulled up stakes and moved to <placeName>Carlisle, Pennsylvania</placeName>. Twenty-
two thousand graduates had completed the <org>Army</org> program.</div>
<div> 
   As early as <date>September</date> <date>1945</date>, veterans began to drift back to college.
By second semester, they became more numerous, along with transfer
students. In <date>April</date> <date>1946</date>, the university sanctioned Rush Week. At this
stage, many fraternities, including the <org>Betas</org>, had not taken over their old
houses completely, although they used the bars and lounges for week-
end parties and for Finals Weekend.</div>
<div>
   By <date when ="1945-25-12">Christmas 1945</date>, the veterans had already organized the campus,
aided in part by the new phenomenon of the day, the student wife. In
record time, it seems, they had renewed fraternal ties, reinvigorated <org>stu-
dent government</org>, reformed the <org>Assimilation Committee</org>, re-established
prestigious organizations like the <org>Cotillion Club</org>, <org>the White Friars</org>, and
<org>the "13" Society</org>, and publications like <org>the Calyx</org> and the <org>Ring-tum-Phi</org>.In
Red Square, the brothers spent much of the summer of <date>1946</date> repairing
the fraternities. Some found that military occupation of Red Square had
not been easy on the houses. They returned to discover broken doors,
holes and cracks in the walls, wallpaper ripped, paint cracked, and floors
scratched and worn. As one returning vet reported, the floors had to be
sanded and finished throughout the whole house, because <q>"for two and
a half years of GI shoes, without protective covering of any kind, ruined
them."</q> When fall term began in <date>1946</date>, the houses were in shape for Rush
Week which ended on <date>September 22</date>.</div>
<div>
   The <org>Beta</org> alumni secretary, <persName>Stew Epley</persName>, a decorated <org>Air Corps</org> vet-
eran and later treasurer of <placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName>, reported on such things
to <org>Alpha Rho chapter alumni</org>. It is clear, however, that hanging over a
busy campus, one that was full of life, was a shadow: the fond memories
of brothers who had not returned from the war. The <org>Betas</org> lost three:
<persName>Doug Jamieson</persName>, killed in <date>December</date> <date>1944</date> while serving with the <org>78th
Division</org>; <persName>"Hoot" Gibson</persName>, late of the <org>Seventh Army</org>, lost in <placeName>France</placeName>; and
<persName>William Hood</persName>, killed during the Italian campaign.</div>
<div>
   Those who did return, or who enrolled for the first time, found a uni-
versity that was dedicated to <q>"the reconstruction of its normal life and
academic program as speedily as possible."</q> An accelerated program,</div>
<div>
   <pb n="14"/> </div>

   <div>
      including summer school, allowed students to begin work in <date>September</date>,
<date>February</date>, or <date>June</date>, and in some cases, in the middle of terms, <date>November
15</date>, <date>April 1</date>, or <date>July 20</date>. The school buckled down to give veterans the
opportunity to complete college with dispatch, and an average cost for a
comfortable year at the college, including tuition, books, room, board,
and incidental expenses was tabulated at just over $800.</div>
<div> 
   In the autumn of <date>1946</date>, the <org>football team</org> reappeared after a four-
year hiatus. It reflected the tone of the student body and was made up
mainly of freshmen. It faced some powerful competition from schools
that had continued football during the war, and it employed a fast-
paced, gamble-filled T:formation that scored more points than any
<placeName>Washington and Lee</placeName> team since 1929. It rolled up the highest offensive
yardage totals in the nation-and it only won two games.</div>
<div> 
   That team serves as a metaphor for that generation of <placeName>Washington
and Lee</placeName> men and the <placeName>W and L</placeName> spirit in general during the war. Like the uni-
versity during the war, the fellows who came back after the conflict dis-
played a spirit that runs like a thread through the history of this place: a
willingness to scratch, to struggle, and to persevere; to buckle down, to
prosper, to survive.




</body>
</TEI>
