<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Red House</title>
        <author>Dr. Francis Lee Thurman</author>
        <editor>Leslie Lyle Campbell</editor>
        <respStmt>
            <resp rend="bold">Treasurer</resp>
            <name>Earl S. Mattingly</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
            <resp rend="bold">Librarian</resp>
            <name>Dr. E. Pendleton Tompkins</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
            <resp rend="bold">Encoding</resp>
            <name>Mackenzie Brooks (Associate Professor &amp; Digital Humanities Librarian)</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Rockbridge Historical Society</publisher>
        <date>1941</date>
        <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">This material is made available for use in research, teaching, and private study, pursuant to U.S. Copyright law. The user assumes full responsibility for any use of the materials, including but not limited to, infringement of copyright and publication rights of reproduced materials. Any materials used should be fully credited with the source. Permission for publication of this material, in part or in full, must be secured with the Head of Special Collections.</availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <p>The first regular quarterly meeting of the Rockbridge Historical Society was held in the Washington and Lee Student Union building, on October 23, 1939. At this meeting, Dr. Francis Lee Thurman read the following paper on the “Red House,” the old home of John McDowell, and the present home of Mrs. J. G. Alexander, near Fairfield, Va.</p>
  </front>
<body>
      <p>Old houses in the Valley of Virginia are not so old as those in <placeName>Tidewater</placeName>, but there are some of them of very great importance as keystones in history. <placeName>Red House</placeName> is one of these.
    <note n="1">This is a <ref target="http://www.google.com">note!</ref><lb />THis is a second line</note></p>
      <p>After the siege of Londonderry, many Scotch-Irish emigrated to America, first to Pennsylvania, and later, to the Valley of Virginia. <persName ref="http://www.google.com"><forename>John</forename> <surname>Lewis</surname></persName>, who settled in Augusta and founded Staunton, Virginia, attracted many prominent families to the Valley, and among them were his cousins, the McDowells, the Greenlees, the McClungs, the Mackeys, etc. They came up the Valley from Harper's Ferry and the <placeName ref="http://www.google.com">Winchester Country</placeName>, and when they arrived at Staunton they were attracted by the much heralded allurements of the Borden Grant, which, on one side joined the great Beverley Grant. Benjamin Borden met up with them at Staunton, and steered them to his Grant. The venerable Ephraim McDowell, his daughter, Mary Greenlee, and her husband, James Greenlee, his sons, James and John McDowell, and the latter’s wife, Magdalena Woods, were the first emigrants. Borden offered John McDowell one thousand acres of land, of his own selection, situated where he wished, to survey these lands for him. John and Magdalena Woods had been married perhaps in Ireland, and had a child or two at this time. He selected the site of Red House and one thousand acres around it as his habitat. Old Ephraim had lands adjoining, and James and Mary Greenlee also settled nearby. James McDowell did not remain here, but went on to North Carolina and became the progenitor of all that very large and rather distinguished North Carolina branch. John built <pb /> a large log house, and different from his neighbors, skinned the logs, so that they presented a white appearance. On the back side of his lands was a vein of red ochre, and from this he obtained a lot of powdered material, which, when mixed with water, made a red paint, and with this he painted the logs. This being the only one hereabouts thus decorated, it was called the Red House.<note n="2">Sample comment #2</note> Here he lived the hardy life of the pioneer, and here his sons, Samuel and James grew apace. His arrival here was in October 1737, and he immediately built his habitat before the winter came on. Samuel was the older of the boys, and often carried the chain during the surveys
made for Benjamin Borden, in the Borden Grant. Thus it was that he became an important witness in boundaries disputes, which were frequent. John was a man of substance and importance, and was made Captain of the Militia Company, formed for protective purposes against the Indians. In 1742, Iroquois Indians from New
York came through here on their way South to fight the Cherokees, or Choctaws, and camped for some days near the Red House. Indians always lived off the land through which they went, as they had no commissaries, and having been plied with much liquor, became quite obnoxious, killing a hog here, and a cow there with their arrows, as if these animals were public property. Col. Patton, of
Pattonsburg, on the James River, was County Lieutenant, and upon hearing of these depredations, ordered Capt. McDowell to assemble his militia, and escort them through the territory. This was being accomplished peaceably, when a lame Indian, who could not keep up with the cavaleade, stepped out of the path, or
trail, for some purpose, and a degenerate white man, without rhyme or reason,shot off his gun, either at him or to scare him,  and he immediately gave a war whoop, and the battle was on. The Chief whirled and shot Capt. McDowell, who was riding beside him, and somebody else shot the Chief. In a little while seven or
eight Whites were killed, and about seventeen or eighteen Indians, when the rest took to the mountains, and returned to New York. This fight occurred on Balcony Downs, and the little stream where it took place is still called Battle Creek. This was the first fight between the Whites and Indians in the County. The widow of Capt. McDowell continued to live on at Red House with her
sons, Samuel and James, and her daughter Martha, who later married George Moffett of Augusta County, and became the progenitor of that very extensive and distinguished family.<note place="side" id="3">Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.Sample comment.</note></p>
<p>
  After a few years, the elder Benjamin Borden having died, his son, Benjamin, Jr., who inherited the major portion of the ninety-six thousand acres grant, came acourting the widow McDowell. She did not look upon his suit with favor at first, but eventually accepted him. They are supposed to have continued to live on at Red House until Samuel and James grew to manhood, and Samuel married a Miss McClung and took possession, while his mother went with her husband to the farther edge of his grant, where he had prepared a
  home for her, which is still standing near the Augusta line. In the meantime, James married a Miss Preston, a granddaughter of Gen. William Campbell of King’s Mountain fame, and built a house on his portion of his father’s land, and called it Cherry Grove. Here was born James McDowell, Jr., later a member
  of Congress and Governor of Virginia. His sister, Elizabeth, married at Cherry Grove, Thomas H. Benton, who later became so celebrated as the Senator from Missouri. <note >Sample comment with no attributes.</note>A daughter of Thomas H. Benton married Gen. John C. Fremont, the man who, more than anybody else, took California and much other territory from Mexico, for the United States. These personalities of Cherry Grove were so noted and important that we thought it necessary to digress from Red House, and mention them.
</p>
<p>
  Coming back to Red House, we find Samuel and his family in full possession, and here in 1771 was born his son,
  Ephriam, who later became the most distinguished surgeon
  in the new world, and in Danville, Kentucky, performed
  the first ovariotomy ever performed anywhere, and con-
  ferred a boon to women before undreamed of. He was the
  first man who ever dared invade the sacred precincts of the
  abdomen.<note place="end" id="n5">Sample comment</note>
</p>
<p>Samuel McDowell became a Colonel in the Revolution
and commanded a body of militia at the Battle of Guilford
Court House. He was also in the Virginia Legislature. The
virgin soil of Kentucky, and the unlimited opportunities
there, caused him, in 1783, to migrate to that State, and as
the Law was his chosen profession, he had not been there
long before he was appointed a judge, and became one of
great note. At the same time, his son became the greatest
surgeon in the new world. When he left Virginia, Red House
and the Red House lands were sold to the Treavy family,
and in 1778, Mr. Treavy built the present stately commodi-
ous and elegant mansion, somewhat in the front, and to the
side, of the original Red House. It was built as a combina-
tion house and tavern, and was a noted stage stop for many
years. The great room on the right side of the hall was at
first the depth of the entire house, with an immense fire-
place with pot hooks and hangers, but later was divided
into three rooms, the outlines of which show on the wainscoating
and the floor. One of these rooms was known as
the depository for saddles, saddlebags, and valuables, where
they could be safely taken care of over night. A second
one was the tap room, where the inner man was refreshed,
and the middle one, with the large fire-place, was used
as a sort of loafing, or sitting room. The woodwork of the
old house is very good, and the original flooring is still
used throughout. The Layman Family came into possession of this fine old property by marriage, but it was later
bought by Dr. John H. Alexander, the grandfather of the
present owner. <note place="end" id="n6">Sample comment</note>This grand old place is beautifully furnished
in mahogany and lovely hangings, and is one of the show
places of the Valley. In the nearby cemetery lie buried
many generations of the McDowells, and a fine monument
stands in the middle of the inclosure to Gov. James McDowell and his grandfather, John McDowell, who was
killed by the Indians at Balcony Downs in 1742.<note place="end" id="n7">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n8">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n9">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n10">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n11">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n12">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>
<note place="end" id="n13">Sample that is very very very longn.comment</note>


</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
